<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nullity of the prelatique clergy, and Church of England further discovered in answer to the plaine prevarication, or vaine presumption of D. John Bramhall in his booke, intituled, The consecration and succession of Protestant bishops justified, &amp;c. : and that most true story of the first Protestant bishops ordination at the Nagshead verified their fabulous consecration at Lambeth vvith the forgery of Masons records cleerely detected / by N.N.</title>
            <author>Talbot, Peter, 1620-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17287141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17287141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1103:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nullity of the prelatique clergy, and Church of England further discovered in answer to the plaine prevarication, or vaine presumption of D. John Bramhall in his booke, intituled, The consecration and succession of Protestant bishops justified, &amp;c. : and that most true story of the first Protestant bishops ordination at the Nagshead verified their fabulous consecration at Lambeth vvith the forgery of Masons records cleerely detected / by N.N.</title>
                  <author>Talbot, Peter, 1620-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printhed [sic] at Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LIX [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Peter Talbot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663. --  Consecration and succession of Protestant bishops justified.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Apostolic succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106316:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NULLITY Of the Prelatique Clergy, and Church of England <hi>Further diſcovered</hi> In anſwer to the plaine prevarication, or vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne preſumption of D. <hi>John Bramhall</hi> in his Booke, intituled <hi>The Conſecration and ſucceſſion of Proteſtant Bishops justified, &amp;c.</hi> AND <hi>That moſt true ſtory of the firſt Proteſtant Bishops Ordination at the Nagshead verified their fabulous Conſecration at</hi> Lambeth <hi>vvith the forgery of</hi> Maſons <hi>Records cleerely detected by</hi> N. N.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non miſi eos, &amp; non precepi eis, neque locutus ſum ad eos: viſionem mendacem, &amp; divinationem, &amp; fraudulentiam, &amp; ſeductionem cordis ſui, prophetant vobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Jerem. <hi>14.14.</hi>
               </bibl> 
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>J ſent them not, and I commanded them not, neither have I ſpoken vnto them; lying viſion, and deceitfull guilfulnes, and ſeduction of their ovvne heart they prophecie vnto you.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jerem. 14. v. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Antwerp, in the yeare M.DC.LIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106316:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106316:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE CONTAINING <hi>The State of the Controverſy, and the Summe of the Authors rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons produced in the Treatiſe of the nature of Catholique faith, and Hereſy; with ſome reflexions vpon D.</hi> Bramhalls <hi>impertinent digreſsions and expreſsions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſecond Chapter of a booke printed an. 1657. and intituled, <hi>A Treatiſe of the Nature of Catholique faith, and Hereſy:</hi> Was occaſionaly proved that the English Proteſtant Bishops were never validly, or in very deed ordained. And albeit the proofs were ſo cleere, as to make the nullity of their Clergy, and conſequently of their Church, manifeſt to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any vnpartial diſintereſſed Reader; y yet I vvas content to preſſe
<pb facs="tcp:106316:3"/>him no further then to an vndemiable doubt, this being, ſufficient for my purpoſe, becauſe a doubtfull Clergy is to the effect i intended as good as no Clergy; for a doubtfull Clergy makes a doubtfull Church, and a doubtfull Church is no Church, as giving no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance to Chriſtian faith. The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments reduced to a brief ſumme, were as follovveth.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Firſt, the Catholique Doctors, as <hi>Stapleton, Harding, Briſtouw, Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> &amp;c. in their bookes printed, ſome but fiue, or ſix yeares, ſome not long afther the pretended ordination of M. <hi>Parker</hi> of Canterbury, and his fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves, (vpon vvhoſe conſecration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly depends the prelatique Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of England) preſſed theſe very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons frequently, and earneſtly, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke good their conſecration, to shevv hovv, and by vvhom they received e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal orders; and yet none of them could cleere this point, either by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, vvitneſſes, or any circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; much leſs ever mentioned the nevv <hi>Records,</hi> produced by M. <hi>Maſon</hi> fifty yeares after, of their conſecration
<pb facs="tcp:106316:3"/>at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> by certaine perſons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be Bishops; vvhich they, being in their vvits, vvould never have failed to have donne, if there had bin any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Secondly, that theſe Records, vvher vpon they vvholy rely, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be forged, not only by their not appearing in ſo vrgent neceſſity, but alſo by the manifeſt incoherence of the Prelatique Authors that writ of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of the foreſaid <hi>Parker,</hi> and his fellovves, vvith reference to the ſaid records; diſagreeing in the perſons of the Conſecrators, and in the time of their conſecration. Beſides, the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ancient, and learned perſons at the firſt appareance of theſe nevv found vnheard of Regiſters, and the exception made againſt them by <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert,</hi> an ancient and knovving man and namely thoſe vvho vvhere permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have ſight of them; but denied after to peruſe them vvith leaſure, as they requeſted. Furthermore, if thoſe Records vvere true, hovv could it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve bin objected, that the ordination vvas not only not canonical, but not
<pb facs="tcp:106316:4"/>ſo much as legal, contrary to the very lavves of the land; wheras the Records make it ſo preciſe, and formal in this later point, that there vvas no place of cavilling. Beſides, the falſefying of Records is a thing neither hard, nor vnheard of, and eaſily preſumed in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that ſo groſſely corrupt Scripture, and Fathers, a crime both more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and more diſcoverable. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is incredible, that <hi>Iohn Stow</hi> should have concealed ſuch a ſolemne buiſneſſe, as <hi>Parkers</hi> conſecration at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> hapening in is ovvne tyme, and having related the conſecration of Cardinal <hi>Poole,</hi> Predeceſſor to <hi>Parker,</hi> and making it the greateſt part of his buiſneſſe, the chooſing of Mayors of London, the creation of Lords, and ſuch kinde of ſtuffe ſuitable to ſuch a vvriter.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Thirdly, that no man of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or common ſenſe can imagine, that the Catholique Doctors of thoſe times, vvho had ſuch care of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as to ſuffer ſo much as they did vpon that account, should vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully damne their ſoules, by obliging
<pb facs="tcp:106316:4"/>poſterity vpon miſinformation, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordaine thoſe that had bin validly, or dained before; for, it is a known <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> wherein the Catholique Moraliſts, though infinite in number in theſe later ages vnanimouſly agree, that we can not, without commiting a damnable ſinne, no more reordaine, then rebapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; and it is a practiſe wel knowen, that as many of that Clergy as after their converſion have received orders a mongſt vs, have bin ordained abſolutly, and without any condition, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently without any probability of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received orders, I doe not ſay ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically, but even validly.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Fourthly, that although the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid perſons had bin againſt all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ordained by true Bishops, yet, to omit the vncertainty of the matter; the forme, or words vſed in the act of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, are at leaſt, of a doubtfull ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and farre from that certainty which is required in a matter of ſo great conſequence.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Fiftly, by publique Acts both in Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queene <hi>Eliſabeths</hi> Reigne, it is plainly diſcovered, that
<pb facs="tcp:106316:5"/>the pretended Conſecrators of <hi>Parker,</hi> and his fellowes, were looked vpon as in very deed no Bishops. For, in an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Queenes Maries, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts and monum. pag.</hi> 1295.</note> cited by <hi>John Fox</hi> himſelfe, is declared, that Edward the VI. his Clergy, <hi>were not ordered in very deed.</hi> And even in the Reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. after his ſchiſme, there was ſuch neglect, and contempt of conſecration, that heretiques with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, plaid the Bishops, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in <hi>Ridley</hi> of London, and <hi>Latimer</hi> of Worceſter; who being burnt for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded only, as Prieſts, and not as Bishops; the Judge telling <hi>Ridley, as Fox recounts, they were to degrade him only of Prieſthood, for that they did not take him for a Bishop</hi> Now Q <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> ſupplying, as you shal ſee hereafter at large, the inhability not only of the number, but even of the very <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of the ordainors, doth manifeſtly declare the defect not only in formality, but reality, and withal her preſumption to ſupply any thing by her ſpiritual headship.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Sixtly, Authors of credit have
<pb facs="tcp:106316:5"/>related, and perſons of judgment, and knovvledge, have generaly believed, that the pretended Conſecration vvas performed at the <hi>Nagshead</hi> taverne in cheapſide, in à manner ſo cleerly defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in the opinion now vniverſally received amongſt Prelatique Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that they are ashamed to heare of it, little regarding the different Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of their Anceſtours, who as much contemned Conſecration, and cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, as they ſeeme now to eſteeme them; and cared for no more, but for ſome exterior shew of a ceremony, to amuſe the world, and raiſe them in the vulgar opinion to the degree of Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops. Amongſt other proofes of this ſtory, was produced the credible, and publique teſtemony of a perſon of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and ingenuity, who declared to many perſons of prime quality, that he perfectly remembred a ſpeech made by D. <hi>Morton</hi> called Bishop of <hi>Dureſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> in Parliament, wherin hee derived their Epiſcopal ſucceſſion from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination at the <hi>Nagshead.</hi> This ſmal ſcrap D. <hi>Bramhall</hi> ſnatcheth vp very greedily, as though it were a matter of
<pb facs="tcp:106316:6"/>ſubſtance, and able to maintaine their decaying Epiſcopacy. He hath obtaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dof <hi>Morton</hi> to diſavow the ſpeech, and of ſix others of the ſame calling, to ſay, they doe not remember it, and withall a teſtimony of the lords, who alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they can not call to memory ſome antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t circumſtances of that ſpeech and hereof makes flourishes, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, as if forſooth, he had got the victory in the maine point; or as if vpon à miſtake (if it were ſuch) in ſo ſmal, and inconſiderable à circumſtance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the matter, which is in hand. Have patience a while, you shall ſee how much you have got by the bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. You shall find there was more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe it, and publish it, then you are aware of; and that this ſtirr you have made, and was foreſeene you wold make, hath raiſed the duſt in your owne eyes.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. But I will firſt cleerly, and briefly refute your exceptions againſt my chiefe arguments, and contrary to your method, beginne with, and inſiſt vpon that which is moſt material. But I can not omit in a word, or two to put
<pb facs="tcp:106316:6"/>you in mind of ſome of your many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent digreſſions, as farre from the truth, as from the purpoſe. You frame to your ſelfe tvvo opponents, as if ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the argument, or you the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, required a concurrence of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. You are much miſtaken, one hand was more then ſufficient, and no more was imployed. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>You ſeeme to be troubled vpon a report</hi> of a foile you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, vvhich I never knew but by your booke, and I wonder your long experience made you not reflect, that ſuch things might be maliciously told you, therby to sharpen your paſſion and pen. For my part, I never conceived you ſo forward, as to put your ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any ſuch danger. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 5.</note> Methinks a man of your coate should not <hi>blame min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling the intereſt of religion with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſtate,</hi> vnleſſe it be, that ſome other ſpeakes heere by your pen; or that by a ſecret inſtinct you vnavvares vtter the hidden myſtery of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant prelacy, vvhich vvas introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and maintained in England, not for religion, but reaſon of ſtate. Some late paſſages you mention, I ſuppoſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:106316:7"/>vpon inſtigation of others, then your owne inclination, however it had bin more for your credit to have don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne it vpon better information of the truth and with more connexion to the ſubject of your booke; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>in fine.</hi>
               </note> for my part, while I followed you wandring out of the way both of truth; and method, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you doe not knowe what impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, I was in feare at every ſtep, to meete with the ridiculous ſtory,
<note place="margin">Cardin. Bleho.</note> of an imaginary Cardinal layd to my char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge; who hath more affinity with a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ordination, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.</note> then the late Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Lowcountries.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. You, are much <hi>bragging of the learning of your Prelatical English Clergy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 144. <hi>&amp;</hi> 216.</note> and vvill cope vvith our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſt Doctors, and feare not to make paralells,</hi> and other ſuch fond brava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos; vvhich obligeth me to tell you againſt my vvill, vvhat you are not vvilling to heare. I vvould gladly knouvv, hovv many Prelatiques have made knovvne to others nations, that afther Haereſy came into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, there remained any marke or footſtep of Divinity, or Philoſophy
<pb facs="tcp:106316:7"/>
               <hi>Withaker,</hi> I grant, vvas not vnskilful in matters of controverſy and could ſpeake in a language vnderſtood by ſchollers of forraine countries, but he ſpeakes far from the principles of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latique Proteſtancy, from that vvhich is called the Church of England. Was there ever any amongſt you, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to carry the bookes after <hi>Alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, Scotus, Bacon,</hi> Mediavilla, or Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, Ocham, Holcot, Waldenſis, and others, not to goe out of our ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Ilands. It is no wonder yow burnt their bookes publiquely in the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fity to be rid of ſo publicke reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of your ignorance. Some of late I grant, have contributed much to the advancement of knovvledge, each one in their kind, as <hi>Gilbert, Verulam, Harvey;</hi> but theſe vvere laymen, and medled not vvith any matter of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. What can you allege in point of learning amongſt you, but that which meerly belongs to memory, and even that, patched vp of rotten rags of corrupted hiſtory, and ſmal shreds of ſcattered collections, mingled, and mangled, turned inſide out, to make
<pb facs="tcp:106316:8"/>the ancient Fathers in a fevv obſcure vvords, ſpeake contrary to what they have cleerly delivered in vvhole ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and bookes. If but in this part rather of reading then learning, rather memory then vvit, you had come to any degree of perfection, vvhat need had there bin to have made ſo much of <hi>Caſaubon</hi> for impugning <hi>Baronius,</hi> and in a later ocaſion of an other ſtranger <hi>Salmaſius?</hi> And vvhen out of meere shame, one of yours vvas forced to reply to him that anſwered <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> you ſee vvhat a piece of ſtuffe was vvouen, not only thredbare in point of learning, but ſtained with ſo many fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>Barbariſmes,</hi> and <hi>Soleciſmes,</hi> that it is a pitty to ſee, what a ſport vvas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of it by the adverſary, and yet the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is more reaſon to thinke, that many hads concurred to it, then to the booke you vndertake to refute. I expect you should attribute al thoſe groſſe faults to <hi>Erratas</hi> of the printer, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 175.</note> as you doe the miſtake of <hi>Bedford</hi> for <hi>Dover,</hi> and one moneth for an other, or of the Tranſcriber, as Richard for Iohn in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 89.</note> to reconcile the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions
<pb facs="tcp:106316:8"/>of your ſolemne conſecration as <hi>Lambeth.</hi> And yet forſooth theſe ſcrapers of rude indigeſted rubbish of incoherent hiſtorical Notes, muſt be ſet forth in the falſe diſguiſe of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Divinity, vvhom this Epithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te becomes as much, as a Bricklayer, or Davvber the name of an Architect. I am ſure <hi>S. Gregory Nazianzen</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Fathers, and Plato amongſt the Philoſophers purchaſed the title of Devines at a higher rate, vvith expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of their labour in higher matters.</p>
            <p n="10">X. And it is vvithout doubt vpon the diffidence of their learning that you ſpread ſo broad your skill in <hi>Conge d'eſlires, Premunires, Actuaries,</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, Signet offices, Deane of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Court of Faculties, &amp;c. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith you vvould blind ignorant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of your booke to a perſuaſion of your miſterious knovvledge, as either you, or your brethren are vſed to doe in ſermons, and marginal notes, with ſcantlings of Greeke, and Hebrew words. You shall find that your <hi>Conge d'eſlires</hi> and Actuaries vvill helpe little to cleere your Records from plaine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery
<pb facs="tcp:106316:9"/>and that you ſpill your skill to as little purpoſe, as your Forefathers did their vvine, or <hi>Metheglen,</hi> to get the Welsh Bishop to ordaine them in a Taverne.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Now vpon hopes to deprive your adverſary of credible teſtimonies, you will needs perſuade him, that it is; <hi>againſt the art oft polemique diſputers, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 221.</note> to cite Authors</hi> either dead, or vnswor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, or of their owne party. I pray you M. Doctor, in S. Auguſtins <hi>Polemicks,</hi> how much of this preciſe caution do you find? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tomo</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> Do you thinke that all which Chriſtian Authors relate againſt Turcks, Iews, Gentils; and Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques againſt <hi>Arians, Macedonians, Manicheans, Eutychians, Neſtorians,</hi> claimes no beliefe from a judicious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader? when they produce witneſſes dead or vnſworne, or of their ovvne party. Is there no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene diſputing in Schooles, and pleading at the barr,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 157.</note> betweene perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſober judicious Reader with the reality of reaſon, and coherence of circumſtances, and the ſtopping the mouth of a clamourous, froward, liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb facs="tcp:106316:9"/>advocate with formalities of law; which you do moſt indiſcreetly preſſe, being further of from bringing legal proofs then I, or any man that writ of this ſubject. For my part I am ſo farr of from peevish jangling obſtinacy, that I will not ſtick to believe an adverſary, if I have not ſpecial reaſon to miſtruſt his vnderſtanding, or honeſty, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer much inconſequence, or find better evidence to the contrary. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have donne, you shall find vvhy I queſtion your Relators, and Records, and by ocaſion of D. <hi>Mortons</hi> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Reader, if he have but the light of reaſon not eclipſed with paſſion, shall need neyther ſchoole, nor law learning to ſee, how litle credit is to be given to proteſtant Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 134. <hi>&amp; paſsim.</hi>
               </note> You pleaſe your ſelfe much in a poetical fable of the Cretan <hi>Minotau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> whervpon you make many gloſſes, and I shall make of it a glaſſe for you to repreſent to your eyes the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full figure of your Prelatique Clergy; the cauſe of both was a very unlawfull luſt, in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. King of England, and <hi>Paſiphae</hi> Queene of Creete; the
<pb facs="tcp:106316:10"/>Minotaure was halfe beaſt, halfe man; and your Clergy, halfe Zuinglian, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe Catholique; both kept in a labyrinth, both fed with innocent blood, and both at length deſtroyed by the ſword.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. You pretend to shew wit in applying this fable to the relation of your Clergys deſcent from the <hi>Nag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shead,</hi> which you might better have called a tale of a tun, then a tub, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re relating to a Taverne; vnleſſe it be, becauſe your Taverne-Prelates came at length to give place to <hi>Tubpreachers.</hi> This is only to give you an Item, rather te shevv your ſelfe wary then witty; as being more ſutable to your age, and profitable to your cauſe. But I can not perceive how you were eyther wary, or witty, in vpbraiding men of my coate with the ill ſucceſſe of Princes that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their counſel, after ſuch, and ſo fresh an example, which never happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſince God created the vvorld, by the counſel of any Clergy but yours. You ſay it is pitty I vvas not of his Councel, I am ſure it is pitty that ever any Prince, or ſtate, should here after be led by the adviſe of your Clergy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:106316:10"/>they deſerve the like ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. But this fond vindication of your forged Records muſt be decked with more pedantical stuffe of Poetical fables. The Nagshead true ſtory you metamorphoſe into <hi>an imaginary Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera and M. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 146.</note> Maſon was the Bellerophon that deſtroyed this monſter,</hi> this <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humus brat vvas the Minerva, or Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of M. Neales brain, or ſome others who fathered this rapping lie vpon him.</hi> If a chimera be compoſed of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, what can be more chimerical, then your ſolemne conſecration at Lambeth that contradicts not onely the conſtant tradition of wiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienable men, but the very ſtatutes of the Prince, the acts of Parliament, the doctriner of Proteſtants, and even the Proteſtant Creed contrived in thoſe times. This is no Minerva, no iſſue of any braine but an abortive reeling Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus hatched far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the braine, a Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can ridiculouſly halting at every ſtep. Your Bellerophon with his Pegaſus, or poetical Nagshoofe hath only opened a fountaine of fictions when he publis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed his feigned Records, but the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
<pb facs="tcp:106316:11"/>head relation hath made ſuch a breach in your Prelatic Church, that all your Heads put together will never ſtop it.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. You are not content to make oſtentation of your wit, but are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo to shew your judgement in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xing vs of imprudence, becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, with indiſcreete zeale <hi>we indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to make Proſelites, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 216.</note> and follow thoſe birds with noiſe, and clamour, vvhich vve deſire to catch.</hi> Many ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are ſo faſt a ſleepe in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hereſy, that they will not heare ordinary admonitions; to ſuch God commands his preachers, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1.</note> 
               <hi>crie, and ceaſe not, as a trumpet exalt thy voice, and tell my people their vvicked doings.</hi> But why you should compare your proteſtants to birds, I know not, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be, becauſe you have caged them vp in ignorance, or frighted them with skar-crowes of Idols, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuperſtructures from flocking to the field of the true Church. Chriſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Apoſtles rather fishers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and it is the practiſe of fishers to dash in the water thereby to drive the fish to their nets, and I ſuppoſe you
<pb facs="tcp:106316:11"/>have obſerved no ſuch veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy that ſurpaſſes the invectives of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Scribes and Phariſees miſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the birds he deſired to catch. But thoſe he catcheth, he maketh them ſilent like fishes, not prating like par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats out of Scripture they know not what, nor chattering togeter like dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent birds in a bush, every one in a ſeveral note, as thoſe doe, who are caught, and taught by Proteſtant, not fishers, but fowlers: vnleſſe it be in troubled waters. You would doe vvel hereafter to reflect before hand, that what you would ſay, have the ground of common ſenſe, before you worke it, and trim it into quaint ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces which in this particular you forgot; for the noyſe is not vſed (if any be vſed) to fright away the game, but thoſe that would make an injuſt prey of it, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it from falling into better hands.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 24.</note> You thinke I have forgotten Epictetus his rule, <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to diſtruſt.</hi> But you vvil find me not much guilty of that forgetfulnes, vvhen you ſee hovv often I put the Reader in mind, and vpon what grounds, not to truſt the
<pb facs="tcp:106316:12"/>allegations, and atteſtations of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſters. But that I should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtruſt the perfect remembrance teſtified vpon oath of a perſon, both of vnderſtanding, and honour (that neyther would for any intereſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare himſelfe, nor could have any intereſt in ſo doeing) then a negative teſtimony of men not remembring ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon abſence, or inadvertence, or diſtance of time, I can not find ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the text of Epictetus, nor in the commentary of your grammatical Champion Salmaſius any ſuch rule. Had I taken for vvitnes à man that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes Religion vpon intereſt, and makes it his profeſſion to advance his ovvne, and other mens intereſt by cheating Policy, or foolish knavery, then you had done a deed of Chriſtian Charity by teaching me this leſſon of your Stoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Philoſophy.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106316:12"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>My firſt and ſecond reaſon defended againſt the Doctors objections.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the firſt argument, deduced from the authority of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Doctors, charging in their printed bookes your firſt ſuperintendents vvith vvant of Epiſcopal conſecration, ſome five or ſix yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res after you pretend it vvas ſo ſolemnly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> you give no other anſvver; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 167.</note> but that <hi>you regard not their judgment, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, beauſe they give no cauſe, or reaſon of their Knovvledge.</hi> Ipray, Mr. Doctor, vvhat greater cauſe of Knovvledge can ther be of the <hi>not being</hi> of a viſible, and publicque ſolemnity, then the not being ſeene, or heard of by kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vving parſons, vvho made it their buſines to inquire after it, in the very ſame time, and place vvherin its pretended to have bin acted? To ſay that D. <hi>Harding, Stapleton, Bristovv, Reynolds,</hi> and others, should object in print againſt your proteſtant Bishops, vvant of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, vvithout inquiring, and examining vvhether they vvere ordained or no, is in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent termes, to call them <hi>fooles,</hi> and <hi>Knaves,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 207.</note> hovvever <hi>averſe you pretend to be from ſo unma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly language;</hi> your attributing the obiections of theſe great Doctors to <hi>credulity,</hi> and <hi>preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> doth rather increaſe, then diminish the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106316:13"/>jury, for, you ought to knovv, that <hi>credulity</hi> contradicted by publique and obvious eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; is of the groſſer ſort of foolery, and <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> that makes men ſlight ſuch evidence, is the moſt <hi>malicious knavery:</hi> neither of both can be layd to the charge of ſo learned, and honeſt perſons, as the foreſaid Doctors, who would never preſſe <hi>Parker,</hi> and his fellovves, <hi>to shevv the regiſter,</hi> and <hi>hovv, and by vvhom, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Epiſcopal Orders,</hi> if there had bin in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe days as publique, and authentique regiſters, as now yee pretend.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To this you ſay, <hi>that none of our Doctors did ever vrge any ſuch thing, as required that yee should cite the regiſters, in prudence. And that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re vvas no preſsing to produce Regiſters.</hi> What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Doe not men in à ſuite of lavv produce what is for their manifeſt advantage of their ovvne accord? I am ſure you bring many things, you thinke advantagious, which neyther any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor reaſon preſſed you to doe. But that they were preſſed immediately after, you may learne out of D. Harding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſay likvviſe to you M.r Ievvel, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confut. apol. fol.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59. <hi>edit an.</hi> 1566.</note> and to each of your companions, shevv vs the regiſter of your Bishops, &amp;c. Shevv vs the letters of your orders. But order you have not: for, vvho could give that to you of all theſe nevv Miniſters, hovv ſoever el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe you call them, vvhich he hath not himſelfe</hi> Yet I muſt confeſſe it vvas prudence in your firſt Bishops, not to cite the regiſters, though D. <hi>Harding</hi> called for them; becauſe it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by their ſilence, to acknowledge, the want
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106316:13"/>of regiſters, then to prove themſelves impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, by producing them in a time, wherin their forgery had bin diſcovered by thouſands of witneſſes incaſe they were forged then, and not afterwards, when ordination was grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne into more credit. And as I commend the prudent ſilence of your firſt Bishops, ſo I muſt condemne your ſilly anſwer in averring, that the <hi>regiſters or records, vvere cited in print, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 112.</note> and alleaged by the Parliament in the publique lavves of the Kingdome,</hi> of which our Doctors, that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſee ſome evidence of Parkers conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could pleade no ignorance: wheras it is notorious that the act of Parliament 8. Eliz. which as yow pretend (but without any grovvnd, as shall be proved here after) makes mention of the records of <hi>Parkers</hi> conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> vvas made at leaſt à yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your Regiſter was called for and our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors had objected to your Bishops the nullity, and illegality, of their ordination; and the booke of the 70. Archbishops of Canterbury was printed 1572. ſeven yeares after that D. <hi>Harding</hi> had called for the ſame Regiſter, and Letters of their Orders. Though he was a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe man, I hope he might pleade ignorance of what then vvas not as much as thought of, vvhen he vvrit, nor indeed ever after by any, but your ſelfe; vvho confounds the records of Kings, and Queens letters patents, vvith the regiſters of the Archbishops of Canterbury.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another reaſon againſt the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of your firſt proteſtant ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106316:14"/>vvas, the contradictions of your ovvne Authors vpon this ſubject, diſagreeing in the perſons of the conſecraters, and in the time of their conſecrations. Theſe contradictions you call <hi>innocent miſtakes,</hi> and thinke to excuſe them by the retractation of the Authors, who deſired that they might be corrected by Mr. <hi>Maſons</hi> newfound regiſters, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 176.177. <hi>&amp;</hi> 178.</note> which you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to the ſun diall, wherby all clockes, and Clerks muſt be regulated, when the ſun shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth out. It ſeemes Mr Doctor, that the ſun never shined vpon your church, vntill Mr Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons tecords were printed, for if it had, Mr <hi>Goduin,</hi> Mr <hi>Sutcliffe,</hi> and Mr <hi>Butler,</hi> three of the moſt famous Clerks amongſt you, infallibly vvould have conſulted the ſundial; and their judgements, and bookes concerning your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrations, had not bin ſo different. How co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes this ſun to be more then fifty yeares vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a cloud, if it vvas not, that your new regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters might participate in ſome meaſure, of the ould inviſibility, of your Church? Doe yow imagine, that learned, and ſober men, would venture to write, and publish to the world a matter of ſuch importance, as the conſecration of your firſt Bishops, vvithout conſulting the regiſters therof if any ſuch had bin exſtant, or viſible when they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the worke? were they paradventure ignorant of the place where this ſun did shine? Or were they negligent in ſetting their clocks to it? Nheiter can be preſumed of ſo eminent perſons as you make them. But your compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106316:14"/>of <hi>Maſons</hi> records to the ſun, or ſundial, is very improper; for, if the ſuns motion were as irregular, as thoſe regiſters are incoherent, the ſun would be as unfit for a meaſure of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, as thoſe are for a proofe of truth. But if one should miſtake for the ſun à falſe Meteor, called a <hi>Parhelion,</hi> and ſet his clock by the light of a cloud, he would guide the towne, as you do your Church: and men of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingh would be as litle regulated by ſuch a dial, or clock, as <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> was perſwaded by <hi>Maſons</hi> regiſters at their firſt appearance, who ſuſpected them of forgery by the lateneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of their diſcovry as you may ſee in his boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of D. <hi>Andrevvs abſurdities, falſities, lyes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 158.</note> But yovv <hi>regard not Mr Fitzherherts ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions at all. What are the ſuſpicions of a priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſtanger, to the vvel knovvn credit of a publique regiſter?</hi> If you Mr Doctor, had not bin a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſuch pious and learned bookes as <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Religion,</hi> and others compoſed by F. Fitzherbert, and had informed your ſelfe how long he lived, you would not have ſpoken ſo ſtrangely, and ignorantly, of his Knowledge in his owne countreys affairs, nor ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly of his diſcovery, of <hi>Andrevvs abſurdities.</hi> But you ſay his <hi>ſuſpicions can vveigh no more then his roaſons, that is, juſt nothing.</hi> Doth it weigh nothing in your judgement, that this regiſter should be called for ſo frequently, and earneſtly in the beginning of Queen Elizbeths reigne, when ſome evidence was deſired by the Catholique Doctors of your firſt Bishops
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106316:15"/>conſecration; and that neither it ſelfe should be cited, nor any other authenticall proofe therof produced by <hi>Parker; Ievvel</hi> or any of the reſt; and that after fifty yeares it should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, when none called for it, and they were dead, whom it moſt imported, and the time of your Proteſtant Prelatique Church was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re then halfe expired? do you call this obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and forged ſcroll, a well known, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que regiſter? I am confident, that in any pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential balance, the ſuſpicion, and reaſons of Fitzherbert will weigh more then your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that every one who reads his <hi>diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> of <hi>Andrevvs abſurdieies,</hi> will confeſſ, that he hath layd him not only in the duſt, (as you vainely brag <hi>Andrevvs</hi> hath donne to our greateſt Champions) but alſo hath buried him in the dirt of his own lyes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 159.</note> the fitteſt monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſo notorious an Impoſtor. I shall in the end ſtir vp in the reader a curioſity te exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Andrewes impoſtures by what I shall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te out of Morton and others.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Yet we need not any diſcoverer of yours but your ſelfe, you tell vs that the impriſoned Prieſts, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 130.</note> and Ieſuits <hi>vievved your regiſter, turned it over and over, peruſed it as much as they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and in concluſion gave this ſentence of it, that the booke vvas beyond exception.</hi> If they peruſed it as much as they pleaſed, why do you ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledge, that afterwards they deſired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruſe it more fully, and that their requeſt was not granted? What a ſilly excuſe you bring for not permitting them te ſee the regiſter againe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106316:15"/>that forſooth ſuch <hi>Records may not goe out of the preſence of the Keeper?</hi> Why could not the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per goe along with the Records, or the Fathers come with their Keepers to the Regiſtri? Ceer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely there was leſſe difficulty, then in F. Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes peruſing the records, who was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therof as being priſoner in Worceſter. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 128.</note> Whom you make alſo an approve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r of the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords vpon your owne bare aſſertion. And yet forſooth, Polemique writers muſt cite no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their owne party, though you be ſo bould as to cite your ſelfe. But it is more then bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to bring in My lord of Calcedon as confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 129.</note> whereas he onely lets it paſſe vpon your word, not granting it ſo, as having any knovvledge of it from another hand, but in caſe it were ſo as you ſay, that it maketh not much to your purpoſe. But the truth is, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned Ieſuits did never allovv your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, as thoſe yet living, and then living in England (and at leaſt in this matter belonging to their ovvne people may know as much as you, or My Lord of Calcedon) wil teſtify. One as being on this ſide the ſea, I may name to you without danger, and ſtop your mouth alwayes crying againſt nameles witneſſes. It is the R. F. <hi>Henry More</hi> novv Rector of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of S. Omers, whoſe word in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact will be taken, as ſoone as yours, even by the perſons of your owne party, and ſooner in this particular, as having more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to know it. What if M. <hi>Wadsvvorth</hi> ſay he read <hi>Paockers</hi> conſecration in the regiſters,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106316:16"/>doth that make your regiſters good againſt ſo many ſignes of forgery. Nay put the caſe he, and ſome few should have bin ſomething mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the ſight of them, it argues no more then their ignorance of the manifold argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I bring to convince them of falſood. As for your other witneſſes I muſt take them vpon your word, which I have found ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably faile in the former, and shall take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in another chapter to examine them, and what you ſay of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fabulous Conſecration at Lambeth, and the forgery of its records proved by the Statute</hi> 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. <hi>and by the Queenes letters patents, and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. BVt if your Regiſter be not forged, and all was ſo legally performed at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> as it relates, vvhy should our Doctors object to your firſt Bishops, not only nullity, but alſo illegality of conſecration, contrary to the ſtatutes, and lawes of the land? Why did the Queene make good by act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <note place="margin">8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</note> not only the forme of Ed. 6. ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>But alſo all Actes, and things had, made, or donne by any perſon, or perſons, in or about any conſecration, confirmation, or inveſting of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons elected to the office, or dignity of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106316:16"/>Archbishops, or Bishops by vertue of the Queenes letters patents, or commiſsion, ſithence the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her reigne?</hi> If <hi>Parker</hi> and the reſt had bin conſecrated according to the forme of Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward 6. as your Records, and Writers pretend, what need had there bin of this Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? This is ſo cleere againſt your forged Regiſters, and feigned ſolemnity at Lambeth, that you thought fit to omit in your anſwer to this objection, the words of the ſtatute; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 146. <hi>&amp;</hi> 147.</note> and only ſay, <hi>that I repeate, the vvords of apart of the ſtatute, and thence conclude, by which act appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, that not only King Edvvards rite, but any other vſed ſince the beginning of the Queenes rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, vpon her commiſsion, vvas enacted for good, and conſequently that of the Nagshead might paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Cujus contrarium verum est. The contrary to vvhat theſe Fathers inferre, doth follovv neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from theſe vvords, vvhich the Fathers cite. The vvords of the Act are theſe, By vertue of the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes letters patents, or Commiſsion.</hi> I pray M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, have a better opinion of your Readers, then to thinke they are ſo mad, as to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by you, that men should, cite only the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe words of a ſtatute, <hi>By vertue of the Queenes letters patents, or Commiſsion,</hi> to prove the nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, or illegality of your proteſtant conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion. Is it the manner, I do not ſay of Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick, but even of honeſt Writers, to concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and mangle the words wherupon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſary grounds the force of his argument.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But yow are as unfortunate in citing theſe few words <hi>By vertue of the Queenes letters
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106316:17"/>patents, or Comiſſion,</hi> as your Reader muſt be unſatisfied of your ingenuity, for concealing the others to wch they relate. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 88.</note> The Queenes letters patents which yow cite, declare expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, that the reaſon why by her ſupreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, she diſpenſed with all invalidities of the perſons <hi>condition, ſtate,</hi> and <hi>faculty,</hi> and with all illegalities againſt the Canons of the Church, and ſtatutes of the land, was not <hi>her Majesties extraordinary care, leaſt ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance in the politicall part might be defective in ſome punctitilio of law</hi> as yow pretend; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 109.</note> but an <hi>extreme neceſſity;</hi> that is, the want of as much as one true Bishop, to conſecrate the reſt; and therfore she diſpenſed not only with cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 92.</note> and penalties, as the Pope doth in his Bulls; but alſo with the <hi>condition,</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Conſecraters, who being only ſimple Prieſts, and noe Bishops, were by the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes commiſſion, and ſupremacy, exalted, and enobled to conferre epiſcopal orders. The words of the Queens letters patents are. <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plentes nihilominus ſupremá noſtrâ authoritate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giâ, &amp;c. Si quid aut in his quae juxta mandatum nostrum per vos fient, aut in vobis, aut veſtrum aliquo, conditione, ſtatu, facultate, veſtris, ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa perficienda deſit, aut deerit eorum, quae pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatuta hujus Regni noſtri, aut per leges Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticas in hac parte requiruntur, aut neceſſariâ ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> temporis ratione, &amp; rerum neceſſitate id poſtulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. In cujus rei, &amp;c. Teſte Regina, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This part of the Queens letters patent you tranſlate into English thus,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 92.</note> 
               <hi>ſupplying b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106316:17"/>our Souveraigne authority all defects either in the Executors of this Commiſsion, or any of them.</hi> Its ſtrange you ever made mention of a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo evidently contrary to your principles, and to the cauſe you vndertake to maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, that you dare not tranſlate it faithfully. But I vvil ſupply your defect in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, <hi>Supplying by our Soveraigne Royal authority, &amp;c. If any thing be, or shall be vvanting in theſe things vvhich yee are to do by our command, either in your ſelves, or in any of you, or in your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtate, faculty, vvhich by the ſtatute of this our Kingdome, or by the lavves of the Church are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, or neceſſary, the time, and neceſsity of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires exacting this, &amp;c.</hi> You make this diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation <hi>à ſuperflous clauſe, or at most a ſalue to help a latent impediment;</hi> but the Queene, and the commiſſion it ſelfe declare, that it vvas a neceſſary remedy to enable the <hi>condition,</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> of the conſecraters, who were no Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet you are <hi>confident that the only ground of this monſtruos diſpenſation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 94. <hi>&amp;</hi> 95.</note> vvas the ſame excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvhich Bishop Bonner did aftervvards make againſt the legality of Hornes conſecration, vvhich is all (ſay you) that Stapleton, or any of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaires had to pretend, or except against the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of the ordination of the firſt proteſtant Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops</hi> There is as litle reaſon to doubt of your confidence, as there is for you to be ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Did either B. <hi>Bonner,</hi> D. <hi>Stapleton,</hi> or any other of your adverſaries, mention that exception vvhich you father vpon them?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106316:18"/>They were not ſo ignorant in the lawes, and ſtatutes of England, as you would make them, and all other Writers beſides your ſelfe. It had bin, not onely confidence, but impudence to object illegality of ordination contrary to the lawes of England, if your firſt Bishops had bin ordained accordring to the lavves, and forme of Edward VI. and ſo ſolemnly at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> as your forged Regiſters pretend. <hi>Bonners</hi> exception vvas,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Counter. bl. fol.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; fol.</hi> 301.</note> 
               <hi>that Horne vvas no Bishop,</hi> and Stapletons vvords are. <hi>You</hi> (Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) <hi>are vvithout any conſecration at all of your Metropolitan,</hi> (Parker) <hi>himſelfe poore man being no Bishop neither. Is it not notarious that yee, and your Collegues vvere not ordained according to the preſcript, I vvill not ſay of the Church, but even of the very ſtatuts?</hi> Theſe vvords can have no relation to the doubt you move (but our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors never toucht) concerning your booke of ordination being, or not being reſtored by Act of Parliament 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 97.</note> Elizab. Therfore D. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletons vvords, and exceptions were againſt ſome other illegality, to wit, your firſt Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops merry ordination at the <hi>Nagshead,</hi> for no other vvas ever pretended by your Authors, but either this, or that formal ceremony at Lambeth; vvhich if ever it had bin, D. Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton would not have bin ſo impudent, as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject notorious illegality againſt your firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrations.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 98.</note> But you ſay that his objection, and exception sheweth nothing but this, how apt a drowning cauſe is to catch hold of every reed; By your leave M. Doctor, it alſo she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106316:18"/>how apt a drunken cauſe is to catch hold of every cup; and that your ſpiritual Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refathers had a plot to make the old Bishop of Landaf halfe drunke, that at leaſt in a pleaſant humor he might lay hands on them; therfore they invited him to a Taverne;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 129. <hi>in ep. ad ami.</hi>
               </note> this is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Q. Maries prieſts did give, vvhy they met at the Nagshead,</hi> as you may ſee in the answers to M. <hi>Watsvvorhts</hi> letters cited by your ſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Yet you deſire your Reader to obſerve, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 99. <hi>&amp;</hi> 100.</note> that this diſpenſative clauſe neyther had, nor can be conſtrued to have any reference to any conſecration that vvas acted by</hi> Scory <hi>alone, as that ſilly conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration at the Nagshead is ſuppoſed to have bin: and the ſame Diſpenſative clauſe doth not extend at all to any eſſential of ordination: nor to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the univerſal Church; and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners authoriſed by theſe letters patents to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and conſecrate</hi> Parker, <hi>did make no uſe of this ſupplentes, or diſpenſative povver in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, vvhich is a purely ſpiritual Act, and belongeth meerly to the Key of order.</hi> All this you deſire the Reader to obſerve vvith you, vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout giving him any reaſon, or ground for your obſervation. Is it the manner of Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Writers to beg the controverſy out of meere civility? Readers muſt be perſuaded by reaſon, and not deſired by empty words, to give their aſſent in controverted matters. You ſay that the Commiſſioners, or Conſecraters of <hi>Parker</hi> did make no uſe of the Queens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſative power in the conſecration. But themſelves ſay the contrary, (being conſcious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106316:19"/>of their owne incapacity to conſecrate Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, as being only ſimple Prieſts, and never conſecrated) and declare in their deſinitive ſentence, that they will make vſe in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, of the Queenes diſpenſative povver. Their words are.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See this definitive ſentence in D. Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall pag.</hi> 101.</note> 
               <hi>Therfore vve the Queens Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners (Barlovv, Scory, &amp;c) by conſent of the Lavviers that vve have conſulted, do confirme the foreſaid election by the ſupreme authority of the Queene, communicated vnto vs. Supplying alſo by the ſayd ſupreme authority vvhatſoever hath him defective in this election: as alſo is, or shall be vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in vs, or any of vs, in our condition, ſtate, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, to perfect theſe things vvhich vve are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded te doe.</hi> They were commanded not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confirme Parkers election, but alſo to perfect the worke, and conſecrate him; and they ſay that they vvill do ſo, and do ſupply the defects of their owne <hi>ſtate,</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> (which could be no other, but the want of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal conſecration) by the Queens diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative, and ſupreme authority. And yet D. <hi>Bramhall</hi> doth deſire the Reader out of curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, te obſerve, and thinke the contrary.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You talke much of your key of order, which vvas no other, then the key of a celler, elevated by the Queens ſcepter, and ſpiritual authority, to be efficient of your firſt Bishops conſecration in a Taverne, which you moſt ungratefully, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 60. 121. 171. <hi>&amp;</hi> 148.</note> and vnwarily reject, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſtatutes you affirme, that neyther she, nor the lavves of England can make an ordination to be valid, or invalid, becauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106316:19"/>they can not change the inſtitution of Chriſt, who determined for the eſſential matter of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, impoſition of hands. This is very true, but no proteſtant doctrine in thoſe ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as being contrary to the 25. article of your english <hi>Creed,</hi> which teacheth, that Chriſt never apointed any viſible ſigne for Orders, and conſequently it is no Sacrament. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re if impoſition of hands be a viſible ſigne, it can not be (according to the ſymbol of the English Church) the eſſential matter of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by Chriſts inſtitution. If you had vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in your primitive Church the Doctrine, which now you print, you had not only fallen into a <hi>Premunire,</hi> but alſo incurred the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of an Heretique for being ſo obſtinat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your new Creed, and the articles ſet downe by your firſt Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is not to be wondered, that a man ſo ignorant of his <hi>Creed,</hi> should knowe ſo litle of the law as you do. Read I pray theſe vvords of the ſtatute 8. Eliz. 1. referring to an other made the firſt yeare of her reigne. <hi>And by the ſame Act, and ſtatute, there is alſo given to the Q. Highneſſe, her heirs &amp;c. full povver, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by letters patents vnder the great ſeale of England, from time to time, to aſſigne, name, and authoriſe ſuch perſon, or perſons, as she, or they shal thinke meete, and convenient, to exerciſe, uſe, occupie, and execute vnder her Highneſſe, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of juriſdictions, privileges, preheminences, and auihorities, in any vviſe toucking, or concerning any ſpiritual, or Eccleſiaſtical povver, or juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106316:20"/>vvithin this Realme, or any other her H. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions or Countries.</hi> I beſeech you M. Doctor, answer now directly, and without tergiverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might not the Queene by her letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, without any other ceremony, name and authorize, according to this Act of Parliament, any Carrier, Carter, or Catchpol, <hi>to exerciſe, vſe, occupie, and execute all manner of juriſdictions, preheminencies, and authorities, in any vviſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or concerning any ſpiritual, or eccleſiaſticall povver.</hi> What is epiſcopacy, or prieſthood, but a ſpiritual, and eccleſiaſtical power? And what is ordination, or conſecration, but to exerciſe, vſe, or execute this ſpiritual povver, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring it vpon others? Therfore according to the ſtatuts of England, the Queene, and her heires, and ſucceſſors, may make Prieſts, and Bishops, vvithout impoſition of hands, or any other matter, or forme, but their letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents vnder the greate ſeale of England. Which though it be cleere enough by the very words of the ſtatute to any one that vnderſtands En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, yet it is made moſt vndeniably evident, by the Proteſtant <hi>Tenet</hi> of thoſe dayes requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no more for Order then Election of Prince or people, which <hi>Tenet</hi> appeares in their writings, in their tranſlations of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in their Creed, ſo that the Prince in England having aſſumed full power in point of Election, could accordingly diſpoſe, and diſpenſe, at will in any thing belonging to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And when any ceremony of conſecration was vſed they cared not what it was, ſo it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106316:20"/>might ſerve to amuſe the vulgar, not yet inv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the new Doctrine of Prieſts, and Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops not conſecrated.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This vvas the power aſſumed: let vs now ſee their practiſe vſed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kelliſon ſurvey pag.</hi> 373. <hi>&amp;</hi> 374. <hi>edit,</hi> 1603.</note> 
               <hi>They vvere enforced</hi> (ſayth D Kelliſon) <hi>to make ſuperintendents, and ministers of our apoſtating Prieſts, ſuch as Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Grindal, Sands, Horne &amp;c. vvho vvere thought paſte ſit to make ſuch Miniſters on, vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout any other moulding, or knedding. And vvhen they vvanted Apoſtatas, vvho vvere conſecrated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Catholique manner, they tooke laymen of their ovvne, of vvhich ſome vvere baſe artificers; and vvithout any other conſecration, or ordination then the Princes, or the Superintendents letters (vvho themſelves vvere no Bishops) they made them Miniſters, and Bitshops vvith as fevv cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and leſſe ſolemnity, then they make their Aldermen, yea Conſtables, and Cryers of the Market. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 149.</note> And from this ſtock proceedeth all the rable of their Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi> D. <hi>Stapleton,</hi> whom you call <hi>one of the most rational heads our Church had ſince the ſeparation,</hi> gives you this Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of your firſt proteſtant Clergy. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſt lib.</hi> 4. <hi>num.</hi> 481. <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an.</hi> 1567.</note> 
               <hi>And vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin I pray you reſteth a great part of your nevv Clergy, but in butchers, cookes, catchpols, and coblers, diers, and dawbers, fellons cayrring their marke in their hand inſtead of a shaven crowne, fis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hermen, gunners, harpers, inkeepers, merchants. and mariners, netmakers, potters, potycaries, and porters of Belingsgate, pinners, pedlers, ruffling, ruffins, ſadlers, sheermen, and sheaperds, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, tilers, tinkers, trumpeters, weavers, whery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106316:21"/>&amp;c.</hi> If D. Stapleton was ſo rational a head as you are pleaſed to acknowledge, you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but litle reaſon to brag of the firſt heads, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> members of your ſchiſme, or ſeparation; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much leſſe to be angry vvith my lord <hi>Brookes for applying his Coachman to the office of a prote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtant Preacher;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bram Pag.</hi> 12.</note> who by his trade, (not to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of his talent) might challenge an eminen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place amongſt your firſt Miniſters, and wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hout diſgracing your Church, might head thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rable, that D. Stapleton hath ſo particularly deſcribed. But ſpeake to the purpoſe M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: Doe you perſuade your ſelfe, that all theſe fellows were ordained by impofition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> epiſcopal hands, and with all that formality you bring out of your Pontifical? no truly, they were only ordained by letters patents, or ſo me paper of your firſt Bishopss, who practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame ſtile with their Miniſters, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queene did with themſelves, and if ſometi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes vvith ceremony, it vvas onely for cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, not neceſſity, and conſequently with no more formality then might ſuffiſe to blind the ignorant.</p>
            <p>And truly when I conſider the Queens ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, and ſpiritual authority, confirmed by the ſtatuts 1. &amp; 8. Eliz. I do not wonder at this practiſe of your primitive Church in ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Poſt, or Carrier they met in the high way, and that legally without any impoſition of hands, or Ceremony. The ſtatute doth war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it by theſe words.
<note place="margin">8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>And further for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> avoyding of all ambiguities, and queſtions tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106316:21"/>might bee objected againſt the lawfull confirmations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nvesting, and conſecrations of the ſaid Archbis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, and Bishops</hi> (that is Parker, and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ows) <hi>her highnes in her letters patents, under the great ſeale of England, directed to any Archbis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op, Bishops, or others,</hi> (marke the word, <hi>others,</hi> which comprehendeth laymen, or ſimple Prieſts) <hi>for the confirming, inveſting, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating of any perſon elected to the office, or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of any Archbishop, or Bishop, hath not only uſed ſuch words, and ſentences as were acuſtomed to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed by the late K. Henry, and K. Edward, her Majeſties father, and brother, in their like letters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atents, made for ſuch cauſes: but alſo hath vſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd put in her Majeſties ſaid letters patents, divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her general vvords, and ſentences, wherby her H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y her ſupreme power, and authority, hath diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed vvith all cauſes, or doubts of any imperfection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r diſability, that can, or may in any vviſe be obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted againſt the ſame as by her Majeſties ſaid letters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atents remaining of record, more plainly vvill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, So that to all thoſe, that vvill vvell conſider of the effect, and true intent of the ſaid lavves, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atutes, and of the ſupreme, and abſolute authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Queens Highnes, and vvhich shee by her Majeſties ſaid letters patents hath vſed, and put in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, in, and about the making, and conſecrating, of the ſayd Archbishops, and Bishops, it is, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay be very evident,</hi> (D. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 122.</note> Bramhall cites theſe laſt words vvithout mentioning the former, of which their ſenſe depends) <hi>and apparent that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe of ſcruple, ambiguity, or doubt, can, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay justly be objected againſt the ſaid elections, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106316:22"/>or conſecrations, or any other materia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing meete to be vſed, or had, in, or about the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me but that every thing requiſite, and material for that purpoſe</hi> (that is the Queens letters patents, and ample diſpenſation vnder the great ſeale of England) <hi>hath bin made, and donne as preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vvith as greate a care, and diligence, or rather more, as ever the like vvas done before her Majeſties tyme, as the Records of her Majeſties ſayd Father, and brothers tyme, and alſo of her ovvne time, vvill more plainly teſtify, and declare.</hi> This is a clauſe indeed that taketh a vvay all ocaſion of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſcruples, and doubts, not only of the invalidity, but alſo of the illegali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your ordination at the <hi>Nagshead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Yet becauſe you vvould needs have the ordination performed at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that theſe laſt words, <hi>the Records of her Majeſties ſayd Fathers, and Brothers time, and alſo of her owne time, will more plainely teſtify, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,</hi> relate to your forged Regiſters. And to make good your aſſertion, you falſify the text egregiously; for, you ſay, the ſtatute ſpeaketh expreſſely of <hi>the Records of elections, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 115.</note> and conſecrations,</hi> and this you put in a diſtinct caracter, as if they had bin words of the very ſtatute. Its ſtrange, that where you lay to my charge, falſifying of the text, your ſelfe should commit the crime ſo notoriously. In all the ſtatute you can not find any ſuch words, <hi>Records of elections, and confirmations, and Conſecrations:</hi> but you will find expreſſely theſe words, as <hi>by her Majeſties ſayd letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106316:22"/>remaining of record. more plainly will appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> If that Gloſſe is accurſed, which corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicteth the text, vvhat shall wee ſay of yours? Read with attention the text, and you will be convinced, that <hi>the Records of her Majeſties ſaid Father, and Brothers time, and alſo of her owne time,</hi> relate not to any Records, or Regiſters of the Archbishop of Canterbury, nor to the Records of elections, confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conſecrations; but to the Records of the Kings, and Queenes letters patents; for, the ſtatute ſayth: that every thing requiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and material for the taking away all cauſes of ſcruples, doubts, and ambiguities, that might be objected againſt the ſayd elections, and conſecrations, and confirmations, or any other material thing meete to be vſed, or had in, or about the ſame, had bin made, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, as preciſely, <hi>or rather more,</hi> then ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Majeſties time, <hi>as by the Records of her Majeſties ſaid Father, and Brothers time, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of her ovvne, vvill more plainely appeare.</hi> The words, <hi>or rather more</hi> preciſely, and with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re care, and diligence, can not relate to <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and his Camerades conſecration though we should grant, it was performed at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> with a read cloth on the floore, and tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry on the eaſt ſide; for, I hope, in Catholique times they were as preciſe, diligent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in conſecrations, as in Q Elizabeths, (though they vſed not a read cloth vpon à Sunday of Advent, as your Regiſter ſayes yee did vpon the 17. of December 1559.) eſpecia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106316:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Proteſtants Conſecration at Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth is proved to be a fable, and their Regiſter to be forged, by their falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of Scripture, and by the</hi> 25. <hi>of their</hi> 39. <hi>articles; and D. Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hals arguments to maintaine the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, are retorted againſt himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1 NOt withſtanding all this, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſayes, it is incredible that the Regiſters of the firſt Proteſtant Bishops conſecration should be forged. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 106.</note> And why ſo M Doctor? Is it incredible that they who falſify Scripture, should forge Records? And hovv notoriouſly your firſt Bishops have falſified Scripture, is demonſtrated by <hi>D. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Martin</hi> in a learned booke, intituled <hi>A Diſcovery of the manifold corruptions, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 201.</note> &amp;c.</hi> You give fovver anſvvers to this argument 1. you deſire good words. And I deſire a better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver. 2. That <hi>Gregory Martin is an adverſary, vvhoſe cenſure you do not eſteeme a button.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you once more M. Doctor to anſwer, and ſpeake to the purpoſe. Though you do not weigh D. Martins cenſure, anſvver his reaſons, and the examples he brings: confute his booke, and demonſtrations. Your third anſvver is, <hi>I hope none of vs did ever attempt to purge S. Paules Epiſtles, becauſe there were in them ſome things that ſounded not well in point of juſtification.</hi> I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106316:23"/>not to what, or to whom do you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude by this anſwer. But I am ſure, your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-Patriarche Luther to make good his juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by faith alone in his Dutch tranſlation inſerted the word <hi>alone</hi> into the very text, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all originals, or copies, or verſions that ever had bin ſeene before. Fourthly you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Rather then be accounted falſifiers of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vve are content to ſtand to the vulgar Latin in any controversy betvveen them and vs.</hi> Is this to ſolve an argument? Are your Proteſtant readers ſatisfied with ſuch ſtuffe? ſtay ſir, I muſt in the name of convincing logique arreſt your shifting Rhethorique. This was the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. Thoſe that have groſſely falſified Scripture, may eaſily be preſumed to have falſified records, eſpecially when the records vpon other circumſtances are deepely ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but the firſt hath bin the frequent vſe of Euglish Proteſtant Miniſters, <hi>ergo</hi> you should have proved at leaſt in ſom general termes, that your English tranſlations were not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: you should have called them <hi>innocent mistakes,</hi> or <hi>Erratas of the print,</hi> as <hi>Dover</hi> for <hi>Bedford,</hi> which you thought ſufficient to ſerve your turn at leaſt in another occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If one we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re accuſed, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d preſſed by ſundry proofes to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve killed his Brother, and it should be further vrged, that notwithſtanding the crime was enormous, and not eaſily to be beleeved in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons, yet in him it might juſtly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, by reaſon of the knowne publique evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, whereby he had bin plainely convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106316:24"/>to have killed his father. Muſt this be ſlipt over? Would this availe nothing? Can the artificial Rhetorique of a ſlighting pretermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo ſtupify the natural logique of every one that is come to the vſe of reaſon, as not to ſee the force of this concluſion? He hath kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his father, what vvonder is it if he kill his brother? They falſify Scripture what marvel if they forge records. Hath your cuſtome of vrging light conjectures againſt the Church of Rome ſo deſtroyed the nature of reaſon in you, as not to feele your ſelfe, or to thinke that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe not feele the weight of an argument <hi>à fortiore?</hi> Records are humane, Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Records are kept in a corner, Scripture expoſed to the vew of all, Records have fevv copies, and kept by a few, and thoſe of one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The Chriſtian vvorld is full of Bibles. Is it not then leſſe againſt conſcience, of eaſier contrivence, and further from danger of a shamefull diſcovery, to forge records, then to falſify Scripture. This is onely to ſtop you a while from poſting with ſo much ſpeed from this paſſage. In the end of the booke I shal detaine you longer, and hould you faſter, and put a rub to the ſliding eloquence you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve learned in Holland If you vvil not, yet the Reader shall ſee by vvhat I shal lay clearely before his eyes, and shal remit to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne eyes, if he be pleaſed to view, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer him ſelfe what I shal ſet dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of ſome, and direct him to ſeeke of other Proteſtant Miniſters, in point of groſſe, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106316:24"/>malicious, and impudent falſifications of Scripture, and Authours, whereby he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with himſelfe how far he shal thinke fit to give credit hereafter to their ſayings, or writings, and namely, and particularly D. Morton called B. of Dureſme, that Miniſter of <hi>ſimple truth,</hi> as he called himſelfe in thoſe very bookes which ſeeme to have bin dictated by the father of lyes, and now in his late teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is not ashamed to ſpeake thus. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>I could never have made ſuch a ſpeech</hi> (marke the proofe he adjoyneth) <hi>ſeeing I have ever ſpoken according to my thoughts.</hi> He may very well have forgot what he once ſpoke in Parlament ſeeing he hath forgot what he hath ſo often writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his thoughts, and cleer knowledge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>everal bookes. But of this mans falſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings hereafther, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 107.</note> now I returne to your falſe records, being you are reſolved to <hi>convince all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe vvho gainſay them</hi> by ſix doughty argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which I hope to retortagainſt you, and by your owne grounds prove the contrary of what you are confident to maintaine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Your firſt argument is, that value, and reſpect which the lawes of England do give the Regiſters. The lawes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland were ſo farre from valuing, or reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting theſe Regiſters, that they did not as much as cite, or mention them, when <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and his Colleagues were preſſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hew the letters of their Orders, being accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by our Catholique Doctors that they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever bin ordained. And the Parliament 8.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106316:25"/>Eliz. thought it more for the credit of their proteſtant Church, and Clergy, to make them Bishops by a ſtatute, then examine the matter; which reſolution had never bin taken, if any witneſſes, or Records of their conſecration at <hi>Lambeth</hi> could have bin produced in the 8. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Q. Elizabeths reigne. But what marvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le is it, that the lawes of England should not value your Records, when your firſt ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents themſelves never durſt ſend D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or any of the reſt who deſired it, an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique Copie of them out of your Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry? Or ſo muchas make mention of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Your ſecond argument is taken from the credit of the foure publique Notaries, who did teſtify Parkers individual conſecration at Lambeth, it being obſervable that theſe four Notaries were the ſame who did draw Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Pooles</hi> conſecration into Acts, and atteſt them. This proofe, and obſervation weighs as litle, as foure publique Notaries conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and credit, who in Cardinal <hi>Pooles</hi> time profeſſed one faith, and in <hi>Parkers</hi> an other. Men that counterfeit religions, will have no difficulty te counterfeit Regiſters, if they be commanded, or inclined to do it; neither would their teſtimony, be of vndoubted cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in any place of the world, if contradicted by ſo many arguments, and circumſtances as your pretended conſecration at Lambeth. But in caſe theſe Notaries had bin perſons beyond all exception, might not their hands be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106316:25"/>as well as the Regiſter? What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter difficulty can there be in one more then in the other? Its a ſilly argument that involves in it ſelfe the ſame difficulty it ought to cleere. Your third and fourth ground of the Queens Commiſſion, and of the Act of Parliament 8. Eliz. have bin ansvvered in the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and are evident proofes, that your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords are forged.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 115. <hi>&amp;</hi> 116.</note> Your fifth ground is <hi>taken from a booke you ſay vvas printed an.</hi> 1572. <hi>of the lives of</hi> 70. <hi>ſucceeding Archbishops of Canterbury, vvherin the Author (that vvas Archbishop Parker him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) having deſcribed the Confirmations, and Conſecrations of his fellovves, he addeth in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Theſe confirmations, and conſecrations do appeare in the Regiſters.</hi> It ſeemes you learnt from Parker to cite your ſelfe as a vvitneſſe for your felfe. Is this the manner of Polemick Writers? But why did not <hi>Parker,</hi> or <hi>Ievvel,</hi> remit D. <hi>Harding</hi> to theſe Regiſters, wherof M. <hi>Parker</hi> ſome ſeaven yeares after made (if vve believe you) marginal notes; when he ſo earneſtly called for them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confut. Apolog. fol.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59 <hi>edit.</hi> 1566.</note> 
               <hi>shevv vs your Regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> in the yeare 1566. Then vvas the time for Parker, and the reſt to cite them, and not in the yeare 1572. Yet D. Champney doubts whether any ſuch booke vvas printed of your Archbishops as you pretend. Whether it was, or no, it matters not, for the Regiſters cited in the margent by Parker, mentioneth not any place, or forme of their conſecrations, and is as indifferent for the <hi>Nagshead</hi> Taver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106316:26"/>as for the Chapell of <hi>Lamheth,</hi> as you may ſee in the booke called <hi>Antiquitates Britannia</hi> edit. 1605. into which this forged Regiſter was foiſted, being a meere novelty, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore contrary to the drift, and title of the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, without connexion to what goeth before, or followeth after.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But how comes it to paſſe M. Doctor, that in this booke, and Regiſter, are <hi>ſet dovvne, as you ſay, the names of your Bishops, their Countries, their Armes both of their ſees and families, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 164.</note> their reſpective ages, their vniverſities, their degrees in Schooles, vvith the times</hi> (but not the place) <hi>of their ſeveral conſecrations?</hi> How comes it to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe I ſay, there should be roome for all theſe things, and none at all for <hi>Lambeth,</hi> which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vp no more then <hi>Ipsvvich,</hi> Parkers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> his vniverfity? Is it more material to put in a Regiſter, the place of a Bishops nativity, or education, then the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce where he received his caracter, or conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Did he eſteeme more the degree of a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, then the dignity of a Bishop? I could not exact, nor expect from M. <hi>Parker,</hi> that he should aſſure vs in his Regiſter, whether the Chapell of <hi>Lambeth</hi> vvas adorned with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtry on the eaſt, or weſt ſide, as <hi>Maſon</hi> doth; but me thinks his Lordship might have remembered on which ſide the <hi>Thames</hi> ſtands <hi>Lambeth,</hi> if it had bin the place of his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 164.</note> 
               <hi>It is hardly poſsible for the vvit of man,</hi> ſaith the Doctor, <hi>to contrive more matter into a leſſer
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106316:26"/>roome.</hi> My complaint is, that ſo much ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flous matter was thruſt in, and that which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported moſt, (to wit the place of your firſt Bishops conſecration) omitted. I confeſſe M. Doctor, you have as much reaſon to commend in this caſe, Parkers wit for not mentioning <hi>Lambeth,</hi> as in an other you had to commend <hi>Jevvels</hi> prudence, for not anſwering <hi>Harding</hi> when he preſſed him to shew the Regiſters of his Bishops, and their letters of Orders. For, if M. <hi>Parker</hi> had but named <hi>Lambeth</hi> as the place of his conſecration, the forgery of his Records had bin as manifeſt to as many as then remembred the 17. of December 1559. and never heard of any ſolemnity at <hi>Lambeth</hi> on that day: But though I commend M. <hi>Parkers</hi> wit in concealing the place of his conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet I muſt condemne your judgement, good M. <hi>Bramhall,</hi> for citing a Regiſter ſo diſadvantagious to your cauſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Your 6. and laſt ground deſtroyes the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve former, <hi>becauſe it is taken from the agreement, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 116.</note> and concurrence of your civil Records vvith your eccleſiaſtical Regiſters.</hi> There can not be greater diſagreement, and oppoſition then there is betweene the Queenes commiſſion, or letters patents, the Act of Parliament 8, Elizab. and your Regiſters. Theſe Regiſters ſuppoſe, and declare, ther was no need of a diſpenſation, the letters patents, and Act of Parliament de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, there vvas a neceſſity to diſpenſe vvith defects, and diſabilities. Your Regiſters ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the conſecraters vvere true Bishops;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106316:27"/>The Queens Commiſſion ſuppoſe they vvere not, becanſe she diſpenſeth vvith defects of the conſecraters <hi>ſtate,</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> vvhich de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects could be no other, then vvant of epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal conſecration. Your Regiſters ſuppoſe that foure Bishops did conſecrate; but the Acts of Parliament do ſuppoſe, that one perſon might do it, and that one did it, and therfore makes good whatsoever any <hi>perſon,</hi> or <hi>perſons</hi> did about <hi>the conſecration of any Archbishop, and Bishop ſithence the beginning of the Queens reigne.</hi> Your Regiſters ſuppoſe that Bishops muſt be conſecrated by impoſition of hands; but the Acts of Parliament 1. &amp; 8. Elizabeth. And alſo your 25. article of the 39. ſuppoſe that Bishops are conſecrated by election, or by the Queens letters patents, or commiſſion; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently might ſay that your firſt Bishops vvere orderly conſecrated, and according to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves of the land, though they had no impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands; yet to take avvay all proteſtant ſcruples, there vvas an ample povver, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation more particularly expreſſed in the Queens commiſſion to the conſecrators, then ever vvas ſeene or heard of before her Majeſties Reigne. Many other diſagreements might be ſet dovvne, but theſe may ſuffice to shevv, how impoſſible it is for you, or any other, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile plaine contradictions by improbable fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or impoſtures.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106316:27"/>
            <head>CHAP IV. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fabulous conſecration at Lambeth, and the proteſtant Regiſters diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by John Stow; and by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> Tenet <hi>of not reordaining, and by the authority of our Writers.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. I Produced Iohn Stovves ſilence of your ſolemnity, and conſecration at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> as an argument, that never any ſuch thing had bin, as your Regiſters pretend. For, how could a man that made it his buisneſſe to rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and deſcribe the ſolemnities, and caſualties of his time, eſpecially hapening in, and about London, conceale ſo notorious, and rare a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, as the firſt proteſtant conſecration of an Archbishop of Canterbury? To this you answere in rime, <hi>that my ſtore is very lovv, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 197.</note> when I am forced to produce Iohn Stovv.</hi> The rime is ptety, and in the <hi>Nagshead</hi> Taverne may be ſung to the tune <hi>of Iohn Derry, or Dovvne Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but it is time vvithout reaſon: for all the reaſon you give, is, that, <hi>Iohn Stovv ſcarce knew what a conſecration was.</hi> Notwithſtanding his ignorance, you confeſſe that he writ in his Annals the conſecration of Cardinal <hi>Poole,</hi> who was the immediate Predeceſſor to <hi>Parker.</hi> Why did not he ſay ſo much at leaſt of your firſt proteſtant Archiepiſcopal ſolemnity, as he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106316:28"/>did of the laſt Catholique, himſelfe being a proteſtant, and a greate ſervant of M. <hi>Parkers?</hi> Its no marvaile that he involved in ſilence the ſtory of the <hi>Nagshead,</hi> becauſe he had rather his Annals should be defective, then teſtify a truth that might prove dangerous to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and was diſadvantagious to his profeſſion. But that he would not, if with truth he could, grace his Church, friend, and Chronicle, with a narrative of <hi>Parkers</hi> ſolemne conſecration at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> is incredible. Though he was no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, I hope he might write in his Annals, as learnedly as your Maiſter <hi>Maſon,</hi> to wit that the Chappell of Lambeth on the 17. of December 1559. vvas <hi>adorned vvith tapeſtry on the eaſt ſide, the floore covered vvith a read cloth, that there vvas greate concourſe of people, lords, and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triers, and that many grave perſons received the communion vvith Parker.</hi> This much he might have ſaid of his owne knowledge, or heard from the aſſiſtents, copied out of your Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, if they had bin then as publique as you pretend, and he had believed they were authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique. But after diligent ſearch (ſaith D. Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pney) he found the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory to he very true, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney edit. lat. pag.</hi> 501.</note> and declared ſo much to ſome of his friends that teſtified the ſame to D. Champney, though they were as loath to be named, as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me lords are, who heard the pretended Bishop of Durham in the late Parliament make the ſpeech layd to his charge by the lord <hi>Audley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To my third reaſon, to wit, that no man of conſcience, or common ſenſe, can imagine,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106316:28"/>that the Catholique Doctors of theſe times, as <hi>Harding, Briſtow, Stapleton,</hi> and others, who had ſuch care of their ſalvation as to ſuffer ſo much as they did vpon that account, should vvilfully damne their ſoules by obliging po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity vpon misinformation, to Reordaine your Miniſters, if they had bin validly ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before; it being a knowne Tenet of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, that we can not without commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a damnable ſinne, no more Reordaine, then rebaptiſe. To this reaſon I ſay, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 202.</note> you ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, <hi>that if Reordination be damnable ſacrilege, the authority of our owne Doctors may be a fit</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium <hi>to convince our ſelves of ſacrilege, not you of the invalidity of your ordination.</hi> I am both ſory, and ashamed to find ſo litle ſubſtance in my Adverſaries answer; <hi>Authority,</hi> which muſt be a fit <hi>medium</hi> to perſwade, ſuppoſeth two things in the Author; knowledge, and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. If he hath theſe two qualityes, no ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man (though of a contrary religion) can except againſt his relation, or teſtimony; for, his knowledge of the matter that is treated, doth free himſelfe from the danger of being miſtaken; and his honeſty, doth aſſure others, that he will not misinforme them. Now M. Doctor, can you object vvant of knowledge of your firſt Bishops conſecrations, to <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Stapleton, Reynolds,</hi> &amp;c. They lived in that very time, and made it their buisneſſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all your Clergyes proceedings; and though they had not inquired after their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, they could not be ignorant of it, being
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106316:29"/>ſo rare, and notorious a ſolemnitie, as your Regiſters pretend: notwithſtanding all this, they printed in thoſe very times, that neither <hi>Parker,</hi> nor any of your firſt Bishops vvere conſecrated, not ſo much as according to the lawes of the kingdome. Want of honeſty you can not object to men that ſuffered ſo much for their conſcience. How can you then aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me their owne authority, as a fit <hi>medium</hi> to convince themſelves of ſacrilege? Is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and conſcience a fit argument to prove, that they who are indowed with them, have committed damnable ſinns, and ingaged po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity to do the ſame by Reordaining? If your Bishops ordination had bin as litle queſtioned, as our Doctors knowledge, and integrity, you might with ſome colour pretend, that your ordination is as fit a <hi>medium</hi> to convince vs of ſacrilege, as our Doctors authority is, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the nullity of your ordination. But hitherto never any man but your ſelfe excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt <hi>Harding, Stapleton,</hi> or <hi>Briſtovvs</hi> knowledge concerning your Clergy, or againſt their conſcience, and integrity, and your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders have bin continualy excepted againſt not only as invalid, but even illegal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I know not to what purpoſe you cite the two Popes, if it be not to prove <hi>Recordination</hi> is lawfull: But you did ill to Father your enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words vpon ſo obvious an Author as <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 202.</note> I hope Stephen the ſixth, and ſergius the third, two Popes, were other manner of men then your English Doctors, and did both pretend to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106316:29"/>the matter as duely, and to be as averſe from damnable ſacrilege as you; yet they decreed public<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quely, and moſt vniuſtly, that all the holy orders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Formoſus, were void; and compelled all thoſe who had bin ordained by him, to be reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</hi> All this you lay to Bellarmines charge de Rom. Pontif. l. 4. cap. 12. whosoever rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him, muſt diſcover your litle ingenuity; Bellarmins words are. <hi>Reſpondeo Stephanum, &amp; Sergium non edidiſſe aliquod decretum, quo decerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ordinatos ab Epiſcopo degradato, vel nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim à Formoſo tanquam dègradato, eſſe iterum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinandos, ſed ſolum de facto juſsiſse iterum eos or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinari: quae juſsiò non ex ignorantia, aut haereſi, ſed ex odio in Formoſum procedebat.</hi> Bellarm. de Rom. Pont. l. 4. cap. 2. <hi>I anſwer that Stephen, and Sergius did not publish any decree whereby they decreed that ſuch as vvere ordained by a Bishop de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded, or namely by Formoſus as degraded, ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be reordained: but only that de facto commanded they should be ordained againe. Which command proceeded not from ignorance, or hereſi, but from the hatred they bore to Formoſus.</hi> You ſee Belarmine himſelfe denies, that <hi>Stephen,</hi> or <hi>Sergius</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished any decree, and you affirme that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine ſayes they decreed publiquely that all the holy Orders received from Formoſus were void. Belarmine accuſeth thoſe two Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of paſſion, and to the ſame attributs their commands of reordination: you indeavor to cleere them from it, and make them appeare men of greater moderation then you judge in your conſcience they were; not out of any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106316:30"/>to the See Apoſtolique, but out of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to our Catholique <hi>Tenet</hi> of not Reordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; but you labour in vaine; for theſe two Popes were of the ſame judgment that wee are, though paſſion made them practiſe what they knevv to be vnlavvful. If you could prove that <hi>Harding, Stapleton, Briſtovv,</hi> and the reſt generally were men ſo vvicked, and deſperately bent to damne their ſoules to he revenged of your firſt Prelates, or that they held it ſafe in conſcience to reordaine Prieſts, and Bishops meerely vpon title that they had bin ordained by hereticks, or that grave Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts in their time were of that opinion, then your Reader might afford you attention, and thinke you ſaid ſomething worth the anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. But you know too wel the contrary.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Proteſtant forme of ordaining Prieſts, and Bishops is of doubtfull ſufficiency, and that it vvas compoſed by Zuinglians, who contemned Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination as a rag of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. TO my fourth reaſon againſt the doubtfull ſufficiency of your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant forme, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 223. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </note> or words, vſed in the act of conſecration of Bishops, and Prieſts, you anſvver, that both theſe names, and functions,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106316:30"/>are ſufficiently expreſſed by being preſented to the Archbishop, and producing the Kings letters patents by the exhortation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecraters, and by the litany that followeth, and the examination of him that is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated. This is new doctrine indeed, that men should be ordained by litanies, exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, preſentations, and examinations. In our conſecration of Bishops are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo the words that are vttered in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of the Bishops head, and hands, <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur &amp; conſecretur caput tuum caeleſti benedictione in ordine Pontificiali:</hi> and you ſee how cleerly the epiſcopal Order is therin expreſſed: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth our <hi>Rituall</hi> call the Bishop elect, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated,</hi> vntill theſe words be pronounced.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I grant that <hi>Vaſques,</hi> and ſome other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of late, ſay, that epiſcopal Ordination is conferred by the words <hi>Receive the holy Ghoſt;</hi> but I never read any of them that gives a clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſolution to that argument, which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to ansvver, by ſaying, that theſe words <hi>Receive the holy Ghost,</hi> muſt be conſidered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointly in a compounded ſenſe with the lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp;c. Whence it follovveth, that the Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, or any other lay man who answers, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vs o Lord vve beſeech thee,</hi> hath no ſmal sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in conſecrating. But make the beſt of <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> his opinion, it is no more then probable, and therfore doubtfull, and conſequently ought not to be relyed vpon in a matter that concernes the being, or not being of a Church: in things of ſuch importance, we ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106316:31"/>the ſecureſt vvay by adhering to vndenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble principles. All you can ſay againſt vs, is that vve vſe two formes both in prieſthood, and epiſcopacy; but no Divine can take excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt that, if he conſiders, that they are incomplete, and make but one total forme, without any danger of multiplicity of cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, or Reordination. But your forme makes yee, at the moſt, but halfe Prieſts, or Bishops; and that it ſelfe is as vncertaine, as it is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whether the caracter can be divided. If we vſe two eyther by one, or both all ocaſion of doubt is taken avvay.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet I muſt tell you for your comfort, and inſtruction, M. Doctor, that it is not only a common, but tho moſt probable opinion, that Chriſt left to his Church power, to make par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular formes, both of prieſthood, and epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy, (himſelfe only determining in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that the words should be appliable to the myſteries ſignified) vvithout which formes, neither of theſe Orders can be validly confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This is the beſt vvay to reconcile the Greeke, and Latin formes of ordination, and the ancient, and modern Rituals, though in every one is expreſſed the particular fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Prieſt, or a Bishop. Only yours (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it vvas compoſed vvhen Zuinglianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me prevailed in England) makes no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of either, in any forme, or any thing li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a forme. But if you vvold be pleaſed to read Morinus, a late Author <hi>de Ordinationibus ſacris,</hi> who may inſtruict both Polemick, and Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106316:31"/>writers in this matter, you will find how dangerous it is for particular perſons, or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to alter the preſent, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d approved vſe in the adminiſtration of the Sacrement of Order, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to reſume the practiſe of ancient Rituals ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically abrogated, much more when like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, or ignorant ſurgeons the Swinglian he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques cut away nerves, and arteries, and the very ſubſtance vnder pretext of ſuperflous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcences. You will find the danger of negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the vſual matter, and forme, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe termes were not ſo vſual in all ancient times. Nor that your recourſe to the grecian practiſe although it vvere like yours (as it is not) vvill ſecure you as it doth them, and you vvill find the Greeke and Latin v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe much better reconciled by him then by vulgar Authors of your, or our profeſſion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven better then by Arcudius, who gave ſome light to ſchoolemen in this particular. You will find the Roman Church to vſe the moſt aſſured way that can be imagined, and never tooke away any thing that might give the leaſt ſcruple either for the change, or the povver, or manner of changing. You vvill find you have put a moſt ſatisfactory diſcourſe conncerning the buiſines of Formoſus Pope, and his ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding enemies. To tranſcribe all this at large, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s neyther vſefull to the ignorant, who will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand very litle, nor needfull to the learned who may ſee the author, nor proper to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hort trectiſe which without all this doth evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Nullity of your Clergy, and according
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106316:32"/>to the moſt favourable opinion, of any tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Devine makes your Ordinaion in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vncertaine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 232.</note> But you deny that Zuinglianiſme preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in England in Edvvard the 6. time, vvhen the 12. or 7. learned men forſooth, in the lavv of God, and the land, made your formes of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. I hope you do not take vs to be as ignorant in the Hiſtory of England, as one of your chiefe Doctors did a Gentlewoeman, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely in Paris; when (hearing of her inclinations to Catholique religion) he diſſuaded her from it, by aſſuring her, that it vvas not the ancient faith of England, nor ever profeſſed in that Kingdome before Henry the 8. time. Do not all vnpartial vvriters mention the Protector <hi>Seamours</hi> perfidiousneſſe in eſtablishing Zvvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glianiſme in England, during the minority of Edvvard the 6. contrary to his promiſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to <hi>Henry</hi> the 8.? Is it not notorious that in the ſecond Parliament of K. Edvvard. 6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Converſ. of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 607. <hi>&amp; pag.</hi> 611.</note> begun the 4. of November 1548. (vvherin your booke of common praier, and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sacraments, being impoſed by Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glian heretiques choſen by the Protector and his faction, vvas confirmed) there vvas a great contention, vvhether the Kingdome should be Lutheran, or Zuinglian in religion; and that after foure monthes debate, the Zuinglians did overbeare the other ſide, by ſome voices. And hovv <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Bucer</hi> vvere inſpired by the poſts that brought newes of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments reſolution from <hi>London,</hi> to teach pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliquely
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106316:32"/>in the Vnniverſities, that Chriſt vvas not preſent in the Sacrament of the alter, and that <hi>this is my body</hi> was no more then <hi>this is the ſigne of my body.</hi> Is it not evident by Iohn Fox (an Author of your own) his Acts, and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>Converſ. pag</hi> 372. <hi>eait.</hi> 1604</note> that the far greater part of all your Proteſtant Saints, and Martyrs, were put to death for denying the real preſence, and not only tranſubſtantiation? Do not the bookes which our Catholique Doctors writ againſt your firſt ſuperintendens demonſtrate, that theſe were of the ſame opinion with your Martyrs? But vvhat need we go farther then the 25. of your 39. articles, and tranſlations of Scripture, to prove your Zuinglian <hi>Tenet</hi> in matter of holy Orders? They who thruſt out of Scripture in the English verſions, the words <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Bishop,</hi> (putting inſteed therof <hi>Elder,</hi> and <hi>Superintendent</hi>) were not likely men to put them, or expreſſe their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in your formes of ordination. But you ſay that in the Preface yee <hi>maintaine to all the vvorld, that the three Orders of Bishops, Prieſts, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 232.</note> and Deacons, have bin ever from the beginning in the Church of Chriſt.</hi> Are men ordained by your Preface? or becauſe in your Preface it is maintained that the Church of Chriſt had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes the ſaid Orders, doth it follow that the English Church in thoſe times was the Church of Chriſt? Call them Svvinglians, call them Lutherans, call them what you plaeſe, their Creed, their verſions, their writings, show they contemned Conſecration, and we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106316:33"/>content with election, and when they vſed ſome thing like conſecration, it was to ſatisfy the people not themſelves. And that <hi>Whitaker,</hi> and <hi>Fulke,</hi> whom you cite pag. 233. never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the neceſſity of conſecrated Bishops, no the very ſtate of the queſtion diſputed in thoſe times betweene our English ſectaries, was not about conſecrated, or not conſecrated Bishop but whether one Miniſter was to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to Lord it over the reſt. Moſt of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters misliked it, but the Prince approved it for reaſon of ſtate, thereby to Keepe the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in awe and to have ſo many mercenary Votes in the houſe of Lords.</p>
            <p n="5">5. At length you tell vs that if your ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours have <hi>pared away any thing out of miſtake from ordination, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 235.</note> that is either preſcribed, or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the true Catholique Church, let it be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare evidently to you, and you are more ready to vvelcome it againe at the fore dore then your Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours were to caſt it out at the back dore. Errare poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, haeretici eſſe nolumus.</hi> Your Church hath ſo many times changed its <hi>Tenets,</hi> and is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different for any beneficial addition, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of doctrine, that it ſeemes to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of nothing but back dores, and ſtarting holes, wherby you caſt out, and welcome in, whatsoever is gratefull, or not gratefull to the humor of the Prince, or prevailing faction. Now ſeing it hath bin made appeare, that your Anceſtours valued not epiſcopal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, admitted no prieſthood but baptiſme, and denied the real preſence; I hope you can
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106316:33"/>not imagine, that theſe men would compoſe formes of Ordination contrary to their owne Tenets, and profeſſion: or that a Zuinglian Parliament would confirme your booke of adminiſtration of Sacraments, and rites, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had vvell examined, whether it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained any thing contrary to their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and reformation. And if they had bin Lutherans you gaine litle, ſeing Luther himſelſe in the places alleadged in the next chapter maketh all Chriſtians Prieſts by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But ſuppoſe it had not bin evident, but only probable, that your Anceſtors pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red avvay ſome part of the eſſential forme, or matter of Ordination; is it part of your Caſe Theology, to contemne prudent doubts in a matter of fo greate importance, and of abſolute neceſſity for the being of a Church? There is not a more infallible marke of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, then to exact cleere evidence for obſcure myſteries, or to contemne ancient publique ceremonies, vpon the warrant of a moderne private ſpirit, as you might have ſeene, (and ought to have refuted, if you could) in the Treatiſe of Catholique faith, and hereſy. But it ſeenes you regard not what is thought of your Hereſy, provided you may ſeeme to maintaine your epiſcopacy: and that yee are content to vndergo the infamy of ſectaries, ſo vee retaine the titles of Lords, and Bishops. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 234.</note> You ſay we <hi>have ſuch an eye at your Order, and vniformity, that wee can not let your long cloakes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106316:34"/>and ſurpliſes alone.</hi> As for vniformity yee never had any; and your vvant of Orders makes vs take notice of the ſuperfluity of your long cloakes, and ſurpliſſes. The old Proteſtant cut would become yee much better, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve yee will returne to it, and welcome it at the fore dore of your Church (alvvayes open for any advantage) if the puritan, or presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian faction prevaile.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Pope did not confirme Edward</hi> 6. <hi>forme of Ordination, and that all ſectaries admitted no prieſthood, but baptiſme, and that in Henry the</hi> 8. <hi>reigne, and Edvvard the</hi> 6. <hi>men played the Bishops though never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, and ſo did</hi> Barlovv;</p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. TO my firſt reaſon you anſwer nothing to the purpoſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 63.</note> but only that King <hi>Edvvards</hi> forme of ordination vvas judged valid in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> days by all Catholiques, and particularly by Cardinal <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> then Apoſtolicall legate in England, and by the then Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 4 and by all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and Parliament of England. This you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve by Cardinal <hi>Poles</hi> diſpenſation (vvhich the Pope confirmed) to all thoſe that were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106316:34"/>
               <hi>Praetenſa authoritate ſupremitatis Ecclefiae Anglicanae, pretending the Authority of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish ſupremacy.</hi> I perceave by your other boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes you are well verſed in <hi>Foxes,</hi> Acts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, and ſome what in the Dutch Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiſts vvith the ſtory, and ſtatutes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, whence you gather what in paſſion hath bin done againſt the Popes authority v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon certaine abuſes. The attention to that, made you not reflect vpon, this decree, or arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle (as <hi>Fox</hi> calls it) of Q. <hi>Maries,</hi> made by the conſent of the Lords ſpiritual, and temporal. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox pag.</hi> 1295.</note> 
               <hi>Item touching ſuch perſons as vvere heretofore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to any Orders, after the nevv ſort, and fas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hion of Orders; conſidering they vvere not ordered in very deed, the Bishop of the Dioceſe, finding othervviſe ſufficiency, and ability in theſe men, may ſupply that thing which vvanted in them before and then according to his aiſcretion, admit them to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</hi> I hope this Article, or Decree, made vvith the conſent, and adviſe of Cardinal <hi>Poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> and of the Lords ſpiritual, and temporal of England, doth ſufficiently declare, that his Diſpenſation, and the Popes confirmation vvas intended, and extended only to ſuch, as had bin ordained after the ancient and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique manner in the time of ſchiſme. Of others promoted to any Orders after the new fas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hion, and forme of Edvvard the 6. its decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they <hi>vvere not ordered in very deed,</hi> and therfore the Bishop ought to ſupply their want of ordination. And yet you are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident as to ſay, that <hi>the queſtion in Q. Maries
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106316:35"/>dayes, vvas not about the validity, or invalidity of your Orders, but about the legality, or illegality of them. I pray you, not to be ordered in very deed,</hi> is it only an illegality?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ill ſucceſſe you had in recurring to King Edwards forme, and Bishops, doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce you appeale to Henry the 8. times, wherin you imagine that neither <hi>Barlow,</hi> nor any other durſt play the Bishop, if not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated; becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe forſooth, <hi>Henry the</hi> 8. <hi>was not a Baby to be iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted withall. Pag.</hi> 186. We know M, Doctor, that Henry the 8. was no Baby, but you alſo ought te have knowen, that he was a man more led by paſſion, then by reaſon, or religion. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he perceived, how the Pope was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to declare voyd his marriage with <hi>Q. Chatharine</hi> of Spaine, he did ſo perſecute his adherents, and authority, vvithout regard to conſcience, or even to his owne ſtatuts, that his principal care was to countenance hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Preachers, and principles, as far as they concurred to maintaine his headship of the Church to enrich him with the ſpoiles therof, to vex, and endommage the Pope.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luther. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>de Min Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendis fol.-</hi> 368. <hi>&amp; ſeq. &amp; de abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganda miſsa pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vata to.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 249. <hi>&amp; in lib. de capt. Babylon. C. de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter Martyr in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zuinglius tom</hi> 1. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planat. a.</hi> 17. <hi>fine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D. Horne and the first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Bishops in the Harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough an.</hi> 1559 <hi>H.</hi> 2. <hi>Three Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ of England part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 570. <hi>&amp;</hi> 571.</p>
               </note> Now he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques generally in thoſe days, did agree in this principle, <hi>that there is no other prieſtshood in the lavv of grace, but baptiſme,</hi> and therfore all Chriſtians both men, and women, were Prieſts, and might preach, and Miniſters all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; though to avoyd confuſion, the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Prieſtly authority ought to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome, either by election of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or by the letters patents of the Prince.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106316:35"/>This doctrine they grounded vpon 1. Pet. 2. Apoc. 1. <hi>Christ made vs all a holy nation, a royal prieſthood, and Prieſts to his father</hi> This princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vvas ſo ſutable to Henry the 8. deſigne of making himſelſe ſupreme head of the Church in ſpirituall affaires, and of poſſeſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelſe of its temporalities, that he was well pleaſed to winke at the practiſe of all hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, who pretended to be Bishops, though they never had bin conſecrated: Archbishop <hi>Cranmer</hi> (to whom all ſuch matters were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) being himſelfe a prime heretique, and in ſo greate favor with the King, that (rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvel before his fall ſayd vnto him, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Fox pag.</hi> 1694 <hi>&amp;</hi> 1695.</note> (being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of denying the real preſence) <hi>My Lord of Canterbury you are moſt happy of all men, for you may doe, and ſpeake vvhat you liſt, and let all men ſpeake againſt you vvhat they can, the King vvill never believe one vvord, to your detriment, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance, &amp;c.</hi> There was no ſuch danger of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munires,</hi> as D. Bramhall pretends; who would have vs take his word againſt the evidences cited in the margen, that <hi>only Anabaptiſts, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 196.</note> and not Zvvinglians, rejected ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They who forged Maſons Regiſter, thought fit to name among Parkers Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Barlovv,</hi> and <hi>Hodgkins</hi> both pretended Bishops in King Henry the 8. reigne, not doubting therby to make it credible, that they both, and conſequently <hi>Parker,</hi> were validly conſecrated, though <hi>Scory,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verdale,</hi> (the tvvo other pretended Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craters) had never received (being made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106316:36"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106316:36"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:106316:37"/>Bishops in King Edvvards time) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal ordination. But this shift availes them not; I produce two others, who were called Bishops in King Henries time, ſate in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and tooke vpon them to exerciſe all epiſcopal functions with as greate gravity, and ſolemnity, as <hi>Barlow;</hi> and yet they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declared by publique ſentence in Q <hi>Maries</hi> time, to be no Bishops, nor validly conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Theſe were <hi>Latimer,</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> to whom D. <hi>Brookes</hi> Bishop of Gloceſter, in his laſt ſpeech, before they were put to death for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox pag.</hi> 1604.</note> told; that <hi>they were to degrade them only of priesthood, becauſe they were no Bishops.</hi> To this you anſwer M. Doctor, that they who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de no ſcruple to take away their lifes, would make none tot take away their Orders. You are quite out. <hi>Cranmer</hi> was burnt for hereſy, as well as Latimer, and Ridley; and yet they made a ſcruple to take away his Orders, though they tooke away his life; becauſe they knew he had validly received orders, and therfore was degraded; the ſame would have bin pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed with <hi>Latimer,</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> if the omiſſion of degrading them, had not bin vvaranted by evidence, that they vvere never validly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>We have often,</hi> ſayth D. Bramhall, <hi>asked à reaſon of them, why the Proteſtants should decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne their ovvne conſecrations? They give vs one, that Barlovv, as moſt of the Clergy in England in thoſe times, vvere Puritans, and inclined to Zuinglianiſme; therfore they contemned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106316:37"/>Conſecration, as a rag of Rome, &amp;c.</hi> This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Doctor ſolidly refutes, by ſaying, <hi>It is a greate boldneſſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 195.</note> to take the liberty to caſt aſperſions vpon the Clergy of a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> If it be a boldneſſe to ſay, that your firſt Proteſtant Bishops contemned, and rejected conſecration, and that they were of the ſame opinion concerning it, with <hi>Luther, Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,</hi> and other Reformers; themſelves, and not I, are guilty of the crime. Did not M. <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and the reſt of your firſt Bishops, publish to the world in print an. 1559. (the very ſame yeare of the pretended conſecration) their ſenſe of Prieſthood, and Prieſtly functions, in theſe words. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor an.</hi> 1559. <hi>Protest. Apology tr.</hi> 2. <hi>C. 2. ſect.</hi> 10. <hi>ſubd.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>In this point vve must vſe a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne moderation and not abſolutely in every vviſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre women herein, &amp;c. I pray you vvhat more vehemency vſeth S. Paul in forbiding vvomen to preach, then in forbidding them to vncover their heads; and yet you knovv in the beſt reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Germany, all the maides be bare headed.</hi> This your firſt Bishops tenet of admitting no other Prieſthood but baptiſme and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of allovving women to be Prieſts, was ſo vvel knowne, that D. <hi>Harding</hi> objects it to <hi>Ievvel, Parker,</hi> and the reſt, <hi>If yee allovv not every man, yea and every vvoman to be a Prieſt. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confut. Apol. fol.</hi> 60.</note> vvhy drive yee not ſome of your fellovves to recant, that ſo have preached? Why allovv yee the bookes of your nevv Evangeliſts, that ſo have vvritten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. If this be not ſufficient to excuſe my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and condemne the Doctors miſtake, let him read the 25 article of his Creed, which
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106316:38"/>is this. <hi>Thoſe five commonly called Sacraments, that is to ſay, Confirmation, Penance, Orders, Matrimony, and extreame vnction, are not to be counted for Sacraments of the Ghoſpel, being ſuch as have grovvne partly of the corrupt follovving of the Apoſtles, partly are ſtates of life, allovved in the Scriptures, but yet have not like nature of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments vvith baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper, for that they have not any viſible ſigne, or ceremony ordained of God.</hi> It evidently follovveth out of this article; that your firſt Bishops, who made, and published it an 1562. were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that impoſition of hands in ordination, was not ordained by God; vnleſſe you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impoſition of hands to be a viſible ſigne, and ceremony. How doth this agree with your moderne Prelatique principles? doth it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that <hi>Parker,</hi> and the reſt condemned in their judgment impoſition of hands, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned it as an idle ſuperſtition of Rome? The evidence that the world had of their not being conſecrated, made them vtter ſo abſurd do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and impoſe it as an article of faith v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ignorant Proteſtants. Whether they were Zvvinglians, Lutherans, Calviniſts, or vvhat you pleaſe, their profeſſion of faith showes what account they made of impoſition of hands, which is the buiſines now in hand, and makes them Svvinglians, and Puritans in this point.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 195.</note> Yet you would faine know <hi>how cometh Barlovv to be taxed of Puritaniſme? becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, you find him in his Robes, in his Rochet, in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106316:38"/>his Cope officiating, ordaining, confirming.</hi> Or becauſe Swinglius his firſt ſermon was in the 10. or 11. yeare of Henry the eight, and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſate in Parlament in the 31. therfore Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low could not be a Svvinglian. This is your learned diſcouſe out of Chronology. I muſt allow you more time to ſumme vp your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or to ſave you a labour, tell you before hand that make, what account you pleaſe, you will find that <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe begun the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſacred Orders, though Swinglius af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſiſted more vpon it, and there vvas time enough for <hi>Barlovv</hi> eyther to take it from <hi>Svvinglius,</hi> or at leaſt from Luther, which is all one to our preſent purpoſe. As for his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining others you vvill have much adoe to prove it, at leaſt thoſe you would have: for vve have proved your Regiſters to be forged; but if any ſuch thing be attemted, you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his preſumption, not his conſecration, And for his Robes, Rochet, Cope and Cap, the ſpirit doth diſpence with all puritans to weare them, when they are named Bishops. I hope <hi>John Hooper,</hi> one of the pureſt brethren that England ever bred, had as tender a conſcience as <hi>William Barlovv;</hi> but when he was to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Bishop of <hi>Gloceſter, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 136.</note> he vvas faine</hi> (ſayth Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>agree to this condition, that ſome times in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, he should shevv himſelfe aparalled as the other Bishops vvere.</hi> And yet it is evident, that he vvas never conſecrated, though <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> who were his enemies, forced him to weare a ſquare Cap, and a linnend, Rochet,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106316:39"/>the only caracter of a proteſtant Bishop. Though they vvanted the reality and truth of conſecration, yet they inſiſted vpon this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and cloke of ambition, in their <hi>ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (as Iohn Fox calls it) <hi>and vnlucky conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And that you may ſee what litle hazard your proteſtant Bishops did runn of <hi>Promuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> by ſuch practiſes, <note place="margin">Pag. 1456</note> 
               <hi>John Fox</hi> tells you, how D. <hi>Ridley that vvorthy Bishop of London, called John Bradford to take the degree of Deacon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Order that then vvas in the Church of England,</hi> (vvhich was the forme of Edvvard the 6.) <hi>but for that this order was not vvithout ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſuch abuſe, as to the vvhich Bradford vvold not conſent, the Bishop then vvas content to Order him Deacon vvithout any abuſe, even as he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> After this Deaconship he was imediately without any orders, made Prebend, and Preac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her of S. Paules, having never ſtudied but one yeare, and all his life before having bin a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>John Harington.</hi> Doe you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine M. Doctor; that Barlowes Conſecrater would not be as indulgent to him, as <hi>Ridley</hi> was to Bradford? Or do you thinke that <hi>Ridley</hi> vvould not venture as farre for his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when he vvas to be conſecrated, as he did for that of his Deacon? There vvas no ſuch rigour or danger of <hi>Premunires</hi> in thoſe dayes, as you endeavor to perſwade your Reader: neither Henry the 8. nor his Vicar General <hi>Cromvvel,</hi> nor Archbishop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> nor ſir <hi>Thomas Audley</hi> a Lutheran, and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106316:39"/>after Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> did thinke it vvas for their purpoſe, to preſſe any other ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Conſecration vpon tender conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but baptiſme; becauſe by this principle the King had ſome colour for his ſpiritual heads<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hip, and for the temporalities of the Church; and the three others by diſſembling, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending the rigour of the lavves vvith a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of enriching the King, countenanced, and planted their owne errours in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="8">8. What wonder is it therfore, if the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of Proteſtant Bishops should not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in any Regiſter but yours and <hi>Barlovvs</hi> in none at all ſeing it was againſt their principles, and practiſe, to be conſecrated. But your invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Regiſter hath a property of making viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, what never had a being. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 185.</note> 
               <hi>Yet by the helpe of thoſe Records vvhich are in the Court of faculties, I should not deſpaire</hi> (ſayth the Doctor) <hi>of fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Barlovves conſecration.</hi> I muſt confeſſe my ignorance of your Court of faculties, but like wiſe acknowledge my experience of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of your Court, and Church, in finding things never thought of by any but your ſelves. But where trow you, doth the Doctor hope to find out <hi>Barlovvs</hi> conſecration? I am <hi>confirmed, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 191.</note> ſaith he, in my former conjecture, that he vvas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated in Wales, which Bishop Goodvin had much more reaſon to knovv exactly then we have.</hi> Yet Bishop <hi>Geadvin</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Barlovv</hi> in three ſundry places, viz as Bishops of S. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids, Bath, and Welles, &amp; Chisheſter ſayes not a word of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrationin any of them, for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106316:40"/>of his being B. of S. Aſaph there is no mention in the English edition, much leſſe of his being conſecrated there, though you tell vs that in his Latin edition printed at London 1616. are theſe vvords, <hi>he vvas conſecrated</hi> 22. Feb. 1535. From whence came this new knowledge? It is à preparation, and diſpoſition for a further for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery? Without doubt the next edition wil ſay, he was conſecrated at S. <hi>Davids</hi> or S. Aſaph in Wales, and that indeed may confirme your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of the place, and my evidence of your Clergies practiſe of forging Regiſters. But why you should hope, or conjecture that <hi>Barlows</hi> conſecration, after the effluxion of a hundred yeares, may be found in <hi>Wales,</hi> I vnderſtand not, if it be not, that you are reſolved, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the example of meane upſtarts, who inſert their families into welch pedigrees. So yee, it ſeemes, intend to furnish your upſtart Church, and Clergies want of Ordination, with welch Regiſters; as in an other occaſion you indeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prove your independency of Rome, by a welch proverb. You are pleaſed to ſay (but without any proofe) that Barlows leaſes made in the ſees of S. Davids, Bath, and Wels, were never queſtioned. We deny it. And prove our denial by the example of Ridley, who being as much à Bishop in Henry the 8. time as <hi>Barlow,</hi> begged, as a favor before his death, of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> that the leaſes made by him in the ſee of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, might ſtand good. This you may reade in your owne <hi>John Fox</hi> where he relates <hi>Ridleys</hi> martyr dome. What greater right I pray, could
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106316:40"/>
               <hi>Barlow</hi> pretend for the vaildity of his leaſes, then his brother <hi>Ridley,</hi> both of them being prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Bishops of Henry the 8. time? You are very unfortunate in all your arguments, unleſſe your intention be prevarication of your cauſe, to make your ſelfe more looked after upon the title of deriving your Epiſcopacy from the line of Irish Prelacy which thoug I can not ſay it had its beginning in a Taverne as the English had: yet it wanted as much in the ſubſtance. Had there bin true Bishops in Ireland who could have bin brouglt to lay hands on the new Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents, the Queene might have ſaved her labour and credit of giving ſuch enormous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſations as never were heard of. Beſides I muſt aske you a queſtion in your eare. Were you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor made Prieſt in Ireland? you find an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to thruſt in your being Bishoped in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but I can not find you ſpeake of the other, and you know that no Prieſt, no Bishop. But although you were, if matters litle for your Irish deſcent is no better then the English, nor any reaſon hitherto hath bin produced to make it better.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106316:41"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Bramhalls ten reaſons againſt the Nagshead ſtory refuted, and retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt Maſons Records, and the fable of the firſt Proteſtant Bishops Conſecration at Lambeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. WE are come at length to the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, M. Doctor, the place of your florishes and triumphs; againſt this very true ſtory, you produce ten reaſons, to make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, which I will not only refute, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort againſt your Records, and feigned Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration at Lambeth. Your firſt reaſon againſt the Nagshead ſtory, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>Is taken from the palpable contradictions of the Catholique Writers, who have related this tale of a tub.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> Let us heare theſe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable contradictions. <hi>The common opinion is, that Scory a lone did conſecrate them. But M. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pney edit. Lat.</hi> 1618. <hi>pag.</hi> 502.</note> one of their principal Authors, ſuppoſeth (thus you English me latet) that Barlow might joyne with him in that;</hi> and <hi>Sanders, leaveth it doubtfull, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 33.</note> when or where, or by whom they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined.</hi> You muſt have learned a peevish wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling logique, that makes you fall vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as contradicting you, when you affirming the thing to be ſo, he doth not ſay no, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>me latet</hi> I doe not know. But you ſay that M. <hi>Wadsworth only doth affirme that there was an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to conſecrate Parker.</hi> All others writers ſay
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106316:41"/>the ſame. There was no more then an attempt that <hi>Landaffe</hi> should conſecrate <hi>Parker.</hi> I hope you do not imagine, that we take <hi>Scoryes</hi> ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous ceremony vvith <hi>Parker,</hi> and the reſt, to be an epiſcopal conſecration, it vvas no more then an abſurd attempt. Here is another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of people that ſay the ſame thing in different words.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seing theſe contradictions are ſo farre from being <hi>palpable,</hi> that they are not intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Doctor brings others. <hi>Other ſay, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 34.</note> there was more then an attempt, but they name none. Others name ſome, but they accord not one with an other in naming them. Some ſay I ewel, Sands, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp;c. Others ſay Parker Grindall &amp;c. Laſtly others ſay, they were all ordeined there.</hi> Here we have a contradiction of ſome &amp; <hi>others.</hi> Why do not you name theſe others, and ſome? who are they? where met you vvith them? I have ſought our Authours that vvrite of this matter, and find not thoſe <hi>Some,</hi> or others named or un named? Muſt I credit more your ſaying, then my ovvne ſeeking?</p>
            <p>Againſt your feigned conſecration at Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. I bring no contradictions of <hi>others,</hi> or <hi>ſome.</hi> I name your Bishop <hi>Gooduin,</hi> D. <hi>Sudcliffe,</hi> and M. <hi>Butler,</hi> I give you their names, and their vvords. And though you attribute their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions to the Transſcriber, or printer, the vnpartial Reader will hardly believe that ſuch <hi>Erratas</hi> should paſſe the pen, or the preſſe, as <hi>Bedford</hi> for <hi>Dover, John</hi> for <hi>Richard,</hi> one month for another, &amp;c. And vvill further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106316:42"/>vpon the difference of ſtories recorded, and related. In theſe, both dayes, and monthes, or the names of perſons are eaſily forgot, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me diverſity herein argues nocertainty of the fact. But what is alledged as taken out of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords vvill be much ſuſpected if the Relators differ in thoſe particularities which in records are alvvayes preciſely ſpecified.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yoor ſecond reaſon againſt the <hi>Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> ſtory, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 38.</note> is <hi>the lateneſſe of the Diſcovery</hi> of it to the world, <hi>after forty yeares vvere paſſed.</hi> But this you refute your ſelfe by the ſtory you tell vs of <hi>Theophilus Higgins,</hi> who was (as you ſay) converted to Catholique Religion by refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting vpon the <hi>Nagshead</hi> conſecration;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 125. <hi>&amp;</hi> 126.</note> and that M. <hi>Clerke,</hi> vvho had bin an Actuary in Cardinal <hi>Poles</hi> legative Court, approved well of his caution; but vvithall vvished, that vvhat Catholiques had vvritten concerning the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory, could be made good, &amp;c. heer you confeſſe that it vvas published by our vvriters, and that it came not only to the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but the hearts of Proteſtants; and yet in other places of your booke you ſay it never on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce peeped into the light vntil K. Iames his reigne, and that it vvas only vvhispered in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners amongſt Catholiques. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 46.</note> You have given the advantage of a ſtory, I knevv not, vvhich you are not vſed to doe vvhen you defende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſe in good earneſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But you <hi>appeale to my judgment vvhether it be credible, that this ſtory should be notoriously knovvne to the vvorld in the beginning of Q. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106316:42"/>reigne, and yet neither Stapleton, nor Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor any one of all the Roman Catholique Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, should ſo much as mention it for forty yeares enſuing.</hi> I appeale to your eyes M. Doctor, and deſire you to read in your owne Bishop Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, whoſe knowledge you ſo much eſteeme, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Goodvin in edit. Londin.</hi> 1616. <hi>pag.</hi> 218. <hi>&amp;</hi> 219.</note> theſe words. <hi>The</hi> 17. <hi>of December</hi> 1559. <hi>is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated</hi> (Parker) <hi>according to the rites received in our Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If you inquire of the place of this conſecration, it vvas no other but the accuste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to vvit, the Chappell of the Archbishop at Lambeth, hovvever the moſt impudent Raylers Harding, Fitzſimons, and others, give other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; although Harding in ſome manner may be pardoned, becauſe he related things not before called in queſtion by any, though not believed by himſelfe. For vvho in his vvits vvould give credit to a calomny ſo ridiculous, and ſo farre from all probability.</hi> Is not this the Nagshead Taverne conſecration M. Doctor? Is not this the ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous ſtory you ſo much deteſt? Doe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member vvhen D. Harding lived? Its no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel you should not know what our Authors writ concerning this ſubiect, being ſo ill ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your owne. You may ſee how particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly M. Conſtable, cited by D. Champney, and <hi>your ſelfe,</hi> writ and deſcribed the whole ſtory, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> in the beginning of Q Elizabeths reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. D. <hi>Sanders</hi> had donne the ſame, if your firſt ſuperintendents had not waved that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, and begged of the Queene, and Parliament to make them Bishops, thinking it more for their honor to be Parliament Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106316:43"/>then Tavern Bishops. If yee had ſtood in <hi>Sanders</hi> time, vpon ſucceſsion, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by impoſition of hands, as you did in King <hi>James</hi> his Reigne, not only he, but all other Catholique Doctors, had written as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Nagshead ſtory, as <hi>Holvvood, Fitzſimons</hi> Champney, &amp;c. But in Queene Elizabeths time yee relied vpon her letterspa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, or vpon the Act of Parliament 8. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zab. 1. And therfore <hi>Harding</hi> in the name of all our Doctors ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected to your firſt Bishops: <hi>If yee can prove no ſucceſsion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confut. Apol. fol.</hi> 57.</note> then wherby hold yee? Will yee shew vs the letters patents of the Prince? Though they have thus promoted you, yet be yee preſumers, and thruſters in of yourſelves. Lands, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fol.</hi> 60.</note> and Mannours the Prince may give you, Prieſthood, and Bishoprick</hi> (or Epiſcopacy) <hi>the Prince can not give you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Apply I beſeech you, M. Doctor, the lateneſſe of the diſcovery of your feigned Conſecration at Lambeth, and you will be convinced of the forgery of your Regiſters. For the ſpace of more then 50. yeares, not one word was ſpoken of it amongſt Catholiques, or Proteſtants not with ſtanding the urgent neceſſity not a Syllable written of it in any Hiſtory that could be ſeene, untill in the yeare 1605. it was thought fit to foiſt into Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates Britanniae a certaine Regiſter of <hi>Parkers,</hi> and his Collegues conſecration, but named not Lambeth. At length about the yeare 1613. it was thought time to publishin print the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of Lambeth, at which all ancient and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106316:43"/>knowing men were ſtartled, and concluded, that it deſerved no more credit, then if a French man should now write, or shew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords that in the battell of <hi>Pavia,</hi> not <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, but <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and his whole army defeated. You have not any thing to ſay for your ſelves, but that the crime of forging records which we lay to your charge, is a grievous crime; it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but very ordinary amongſt heretiques. Two epiſtles were foiſted into the fift ſynod, one of <hi>Vigilius</hi> Pope, an other of <hi>Menas</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of Conſtantinople, which was detected in the 6. ſynod in the 12. and 14. action upon reading over the Acts of the 5. Synod; for they found three whole quaternions inſerted by the heretiques, and in them the two foreſaid let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the greate in his 38. epiſtle, ad Palaeſtinos, complains of the Grecians, that they had corrupted his letter to <hi>Flavianus.</hi> And S. Gregory the greate avers that thoſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople had corrupted the ſynod of <hi>Calce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 14. <hi>ad Narſem.</hi>
               </note> and ſuſpects they had donne the ſame with the Councell of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> And as for that of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon, it appeares cleerly the clauſe of the Bishop of Conſtantinople having equal privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges with the Bishop of Rome, to have bin falſely inſerted; both becauſe the fathers of the Councell in their relation to Leo the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, never ownd it, only ſaid, <hi>we have confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the rule of the</hi> 150. <hi>Fathers aſſembled at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, which ordained, that after your moſt holy and Apoſtolique See, that of Conſtantinople
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106316:44"/>should have the ſecond place of honor.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly Evagrius reports this Canon, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4</note> 
               <hi>it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed ſaith he, that the See of new Rome, by reaſon she held the ſecond place after the ancient Rome, should have the primacy before the other Sees.</hi> And <hi>Socrates</hi> teſtifieth no more to have bin decreed in the Councell of <hi>Constantiple.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> And Juſtinian the Emperour ſpeaking of both theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novel.</hi> 131.</note> ſayth, <hi>As the holy Pope of Rome is the firſt of all Prelates, ſo the Archebishop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, new Rome, should have the ſecond place after the See Apoſtolique of old Rome, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all other Sees.</hi> So you may ſee M. Doctor, this grievous crime is no new thing, and no leſſe poſſible, then probable that your proteſtant forefathers were as well verſed in falſifying Regiſters, as the Grecians, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. But you need no information in this matter. And for the information of others I shall vpon occaſion of Morton make it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re how litle conſcience, and ashame your Miniſters have in point of wilfull falſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Your third reaſon againſt the Nags head Conſecration you take from the ſtrictneſſe of the english lawes. But this hath, bin answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the 3. Chapter, and the largeneſſe of the Queenes letters patents, and ſtatutes in favor of the Nagshead conſecration, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Your fourth reaſon is, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 47.</note> 
               <hi>that there was no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to play this pageant.</hi> But in this you contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106316:44"/>the Queenes commiſſion, and letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, as you may ſee in the ſaid 2. Chap. And beſides D. <hi>Banewft</hi> beares witneſſe againſt you in the answer he gave to M <hi>Alabaſter,</hi> that <hi>he boped, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 138. <hi>&amp;</hi> 140.</note> in caſe of neceſsity a Prieſt might ordaine Bishops.</hi> You anſwer, <hi>I do not believe a word of what is ſaid of B. Bancroft, ſub modo, as it is heer ſet down. For my part I believe the whole relateon is feined.</hi> Is this your polemick manner of ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering? If you deſire to be ſatisfied of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and manner of this ſtory, for as much of it as concerns me, that is the faithfull rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you may find it in the Jeſuits libraryes of <hi>Gant, Antvverp,</hi> ad <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> in Holiwoods booke, <hi>de investiganda Chriſti Eccleſia.</hi> Cap. 4. But if you imagine that Father Holiwood did feigne ſuch a ſtory, I muſt let you know, that he was not only one of the moſt learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of his time, having taught Divinity in ſome of the chiefeſt univerſities of Europ with great ſatisfaction, and applauſe; but that he was eſteemed by all who knew him, a man of eminent vertu, and ſupernaturall gifts. He fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retold the future miſeries of his Countrey (Ireland) when it was moſt florisking; and aſſured that the poſterity of the ancient english Conquerours, inhabiting the English <hi>Pale,</hi> would be driven out ef their howſes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, though ſince the conqueſt they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more favored by the ſtate, then when he told this to F. <hi>Robert Nugent,</hi> and others. Being heire to a faire eſtate, and chiefe of a noble family, he renounced all that his birth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106316:45"/>had given, and his hopes, or deſerts might pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe, to follow Chriſt in a religious ſtate of life. Now to ſay that this man feigned <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crofts</hi> anſwer, and printed ſuch an impoſture in Bancrofts life time, is no better then a chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish evaſion, or ſuch a Miniſters confutation, as undertooke to refute Bellarmine, by ſaying, <hi>Bellarmine thou lyeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. You are pleaſed also to call D. <hi>Sanders</hi> relation of the Irish Archbishops refuſal to conſecrate your firſt Superintendents, a vaine report, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 50. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.</note> becauſe forſooth the <hi>Archbishop wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a name, and the fable wanteth a ground.</hi> His name was <hi>Richard Creagh</hi> Archbishop of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Analect. ſacr. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. edit.</hi> 1617.</note> who died many yeares afterward in the tower of London. You ſay that if Conſecraters had bin wanting in England, <hi>Yee might have ſeven out of Ireland, and that your Irish</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Conſecration was never queſtioned.</hi> Its ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that the Bishops of Ireland should comply ſo with your hereſy, wheras it is well known that three hundred perſons of the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could not be drawen to it, <note place="margin">Fitz. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Britan. nomach.</note> either by faire, or foule meanes, ſince Henry the 8. Schiſme, untill King Charles his reigne. Your Irish conſecration is every jot as invalid as your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, neither can you make it appeare, that any Catholique Bishop ever impoſed hands (Macragh was never conſecrated as his owne friars teſtify) vpon your firſt proteſtant Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents of Ireland, who were all made Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, by the Queens letters patents and with as litle conſecration as thoſe of England. Is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106316:45"/>it credible that if the Queene could have found in Ireland true Bishops that could have bin brought to impoſe hands vpon thoſe that were to be ordained in England, that she would have alledged ſuch neceſſity as you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſeene in the 2. Chapt. could not she have called for her owne ſubjects? Rather then gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſuch a povver as never vvas heard of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the vvant of the condition, and ſtate of the perſon, and adding ſuch words as imply the ſufficiency of one perſon, and even a lay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. If she might have had ſeveral true Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops out of Ireland, vvould this have bin do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne? If they had conſecrated Proteſtants in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, vvould they have refuſed the like in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland? though you have no ground to build vpon your Irish ſucceſſion yet I have ground enough in your worke to ſuſpect, that you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve willingly, and wittingly prevaricated in the ſucceſſion of your English Bishops, that they may be forced to recurre to your Irish ordination. Truly in your booke, you have given me ſo many advantages againſt your cauſe, that I shall never accuſe my ſelfe of rashneſſe for this ſuspition of your plaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication, or at leaſt it muſt have bin a moſt vaine preſumption to thinke that vvith petty tricks of auvoiding rather, then anſvvering the force of arguments, and florishing vvith your negative teſtimonies about a ſpeech of one man, you can maintaine a cauſe vpon ſo many, and manifeſt titles defective. What if there had bin a miſtake about Mortons ſpeech,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106316:46"/>is the prize vvonne on your ſide? Is the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſtated vpon that circumſtance? Your fift reaſon is drawne from a principle of Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Cni bono? or vvhat <hi>advantage could ſuch a conſecration as that of the Nagshead bring to the Conſecraters, or the perſons conſecrated?</hi> I shall tell you vvhat? It ſerved, ſeing they could get no better, to raiſe a rumour that they had bin conſecrated, and thereby to delude the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which had not ſo ſoone fully learned the nevv doctrine of thoſe times, that election vvithout conſecration vvas ſufficient. This vvas all the ſuperintendents cared for, vvho in their opinions ſlighted conſecration as a thing not neceſſary, as I have made appeare by the common Tenet of thoſe dayes, by the ſtatutes, and Acts, by the 25. Article of their ovvne Creed.</p>
            <p>Your 6. and 7. Reaſons taken from the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall oppoſition, which you pretend is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveen this <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory, and all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of England, are confuted, and retorted in the 3. Chap. And your 8. and 9. Reaſons from the ſtatute 8. Elizab. and the Regiſter in the lives of the 70. Archbishops of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are alſo proved to be againſt yourſelfe in the 2. and 3. Chapters.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:106316:46"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vvitneſſes of the</hi> Nagshead <hi>ſtory do exceed thoſe of the fabulous Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Lambeth, both in number, and in authority; and the conſtant tradition of the ſaid ſtory, doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the forgery of M.</hi> Maſons <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. YOur tenth reaſon M. Doctor, againſt the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory, is taken from all ſorts of Witneſſes. You ſay M. <hi>Maſon reckoneth vp ſeven of your writers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 125.</note> who had juſtified the legality of your Ordinations, and cited your Regiſters as authentique Records, before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> wherof the firſt is <hi>Jewell.</hi> How falſe this is, may be evident by <hi>Jewells</hi> anſwer to <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> wherin he cites no Regiſters, though his adverſary called for them expreſſely, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confut. Apol. fol.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59. <hi>edit. an.</hi> 1566.</note> 
               <hi>Shew vs your Regiſters.</hi> As for your other Writers, they cited no authentique Regiſters, becauſe they diſagreed amongſt themſelves, and agree not with <hi>Maſons</hi> newfound Records, which alone you allow for authentique. As for <hi>Camdens</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony it availeth litle both becauſe he vvas not ſo bold as to put downe a thing ſo diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious to his Clergy and dangerous to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as alſo becauſe you cite not his firſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which should have bin cited; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106316:47"/>I can not find it, yet I have found no ſmall conjectures of knavery vſed in his other editions, as there hath bin with Stow, and others, this I am aſſured of, that <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> for feare of displeaſing others lert out ſundry particulars well knowne to himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You produce ſome Catholiques, not as witneſſes of your conſecration at Lambeth, but as men convinced by proteſtant teſtimonies, and Regiſters. If this be true, it only proves, that yee never wanted forgers, and that we have ſome weake, and credulous brothers, which is but a very weake proofe of your or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The firſt of theſe, is one M. <hi>Clerke,</hi> who was (you ſay) an Actuary in Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> his legative Court.
<q>This M. <hi>Clerke</hi> met with one M. <hi>Higgins,</hi> who had bin made a Catholique by reflecting vpon the Nagshead conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and M. Clerke approved well of his caution, becauſe <hi>in dubiis tutior pars ſequenda,</hi> in doubtfull matters we muſt follow the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureſt: but withall he wished, that what our Authors had written concerning that point, could be made good. For M. Clerke ſayd that he himſelfe was preſent, when the advocate of the Arches, whom the Queene ſent to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe the Regiſter after the conſecration, and to give her an account whether it was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Canonically, returned her this anſwer, that <hi>he had peruſed the Regiſter, and that no juſt exception could be made against the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>ſomething might have bin
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106316:47"/>better, particularly that Corverdale was not in his Rochet,</hi> but he aſſured <hi>her, that could make no defect in the Conſecration.</hi>
               </q> This is your wiſe ſtory, and your Author is one M. <hi>Barwick,</hi> who had it from M. Higgins.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will ſuppoſe at the preſent, that ther is ſuch a man in the world, as this. M. <hi>Barwick,</hi> and that you do not feigne this ſtory, as you do that of F. <hi>Oldcorne;</hi> but I muſt thinke it is no better then a fable, though I will not make you the Author, becauſe it hath ſo many ſilly, and improbable circumſtances. Firſt that the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne should ſend to peruſe the Regiſter after the conſecration, to be informed whether it was performed Canonically. Her Majeſty without doubt ſpared that labour, becauſe she might have as particular, and à more unpartial rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Lords, and Courtiours that aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted (as the Regiſter ſays) at the conſecration, then from the Records. And if she doubted of the skill, or attention of her Courtiours, she might examine ſome of the Doctors that were preſent. Secondly, your ſtory makes the Queene a very ſilly woman, that needed the aſſurance of the Advocate of the Arches, to ſettle her conſcience, in ſo intricate à caſe forſooth, as the want of a rochet in a friar, at a Bishops conſetration. Thirdly this ſtory is proved to be feigned, by the Queens letters patents and commiſſion; wherin her Majeſty declares, that there was a neceſſity to diſpenſe with Canons; how then could she doubt, and ſend the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate of the Arches to give her an account,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106316:48"/>whether the conſecration was performed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically? A neceſſity of diſpenſing with the Canons, is cleere evidence that à conſecration can not be Canonical; the Queene declared this neceſſity in her letters patents before the conſecration was performed. Therfore she had cleere evidence that it could not be canonical. How then could she doubt of what was evident to herſelfe? Or to what purpoſe should she ſend the Advocate of the Arches to reſolve her of a doubt, which she could never entertaine? This is evidence enough to prove, that your ſtory, good M. Doctor, is feigned. The only doubt remaining is, whether your ſelfe, or M. <hi>Barwick</hi> feigned it, which I leave to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. But ſuppoſe it had not bin a fiction, all that can be concluded out of it, is, that M. Clerke confeſſed the Nagshead ſtory was doubtfull, but ſo that the contrary wanted aſſurance, and therfore approved of M. Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins caution. What advantage can this be to your cauſe, I do not underſtand; though every man doth ſee the prejudice it ſuffers by your ſtories, and pretended vindication, which is real and plaine prevarication. Would any men in earneſt bring ſo weake teſtimonies in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great importance? doe you not make all the world ſee how litle you have to ſay to the point which is to make your ſucceſſion vndoubted?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Your other witnes is one M. <hi>Hart,</hi> who was ſatisfied with <hi>Parkers</hi> conſecration, when he ſaw copies of your Regiſter. You may cite
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106316:48"/>many other ſimple Catholiques that would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the ſame; but that only proves their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, and cleeres not your Regiſter from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. Yet this ſtory we muſt believe vpon your word, wherin all they will have greate difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that read in the 1. Chap. how falſely you accuſe the Jeſuits, and impriſoned Prieſts of acknowledging that <hi>your Regiſter was beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</hi> Neither you, nor any other Writer of your Church, named a witreſſe for your fable of Lambeth, but one, towit, <hi>Charles Howard</hi> earle of Notingham, Lord Admiral of England, whoſe teſtimony M. Maſon would not have valued at ſo high a rate, as to attribute his long life to a particular providence of God reſerving him for the Vindication of your Clergy, unleſſe he had bin in great want of others. But how doth he teſtify? Forſooth, he tould it a friend, and this friend tould it M. Maſon, who put it in print. Firſt I muſt queſtion you whether the Earle was alive, when M. Maſon printed his teſtimony. If he were, why did not M. Maſon get a formal atteſtation as you have done? J am ſure yours have coſt you more labour, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne you leſſe ſervice then that would have coſt, or ſerved him. was he dead? I ſee no more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this then in other occaſions of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable providence to your Church. Will the Earles ſaying to a nameleſſe friend that he had bin at a banquet in Lambeth reſtore the credit of your Church deprived of lawfull Clergy vpon ſo many titles as have bin alleadged, and this man not ſpeacke of what he had heard, till
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106316:49"/>the Author was ſpeechleſſe, and in his grave? but the Earle tould it to a friend. What friend? Why is his name concealed, and his relation printed, if it be not, that he neither hath na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, nor being? You do not believe that <hi>John Stow</hi> related the ſtory of the Nagshead to more then one friend becauſe D. <hi>Champney</hi> doth not name them; and you exact from us to believe, that the Earle of Notingham related the ſtory of Lambeth to one friend, though you do not name him. Yet John Stowes friends had good reaſons, why they would not be named by D. <hi>Champney,</hi> when your Clergy was ſo powerfull and ſpitefull in England; but what reaſon could the Earle of Notinghams friend have not to be named by M. Maſon? Did he peradventure feare, that your Clergy would perſecute him for endeavoring to maintaine their Orders and credit? do you not ſee M. Doctor, how ill groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a fable this is of your firſt Bishops conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration at Lambeth, that you can not name for it one witneſſe allowable; I doe not ſay, nor exact as you doe, according to the rigour of legal formality, but not ſo much as by the favour of ordinary probability.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You will find on the other ſide the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ſtory much more credible, delivered to us by the tradition, and teſtimony of the moſt able perſons of our Religion, and Nation. He who gainſaies it, may vpon the ſame ſcore gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay any thing, that is beyond the reach of his memory, or depends vpon the teſtimony of others. What ground hath any man to fix his
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106316:49"/>beliefe vpon, but a conſtant tradition, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, of honeſt, and knowing perſons? Its now à century of yeares ſince the Nagshead ſtory happened; it hath bin conſtantly related, and credited by wiſe men, as a certaine truth, ever ſince the yeare 1559. It was never contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by any, untill it was imagined by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, that their new Regiſters might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with our ancient tradition, and make the. Nagshead ſtory ſeeme improbable, in the yeare 1613. of which no man doubted for the ſpace of 52. yeares before. But they were miſtaken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe evident truths, though they relate abſurd actions, can not, by any device or art, be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de improbable, untill their evidence be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the memory of men. Time may wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re out writings, and all other monuments, but tradition will laſt as long as men and time, it is a never decaying evidence, that makes any thing evidently credible, which hath not bin ſeaſonably contradicted, when it mought, and ought to have bin done, eſpecially if with much advantage, and litle difficulty.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That there hath bin theſe hundred yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res a conſtant tradition betweene ſober, and wiſe men, of the Nagshead ſtory, can not be denyed by our Adverſaries, vnleſſe they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſay, that we Catholiques have had no ſober, or learned men, ſince they left vs. I hope the Catholique Bishops, and Doctors of Q. <hi>Maries</hi> time, were ſober and wiſe men; they believed this ſtory, and recounted it to <hi>Perſons, Fitzherbert,</hi> D. <hi>Kelliſon, Holiwood,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:106316:50"/>D. <hi>Champney, Fitzſimons</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Perſons</hi> believed it, and recounted it as a ſerious truth to many, as is well knowne to F. <hi>Henry Siliſdon,</hi> a man of knowen integrity, and truth, yet living. <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> and the reſt above named, gave ſo much credit to it, that they published it in print, as every one may ſee in their bookes. Therfore this ſtory is farre from being impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, but is rather evident, as being ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the credit, teſtemony, and tradition of moſt wiſe, and ſober Authors, however ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable it may ſeeme to ſomme, out of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant zeale, or want of knowledge. But your maine argument againſt the evidence of this ſtory, is, that all our Catholiques ſeeme to have it only from M. Neale. <hi>Who told this to D. Bluet? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 132.</note> Neale. Who told this to Haberley? Neale. Who told it to the reſt of the priſoners at Wisbich? Neale. Only Neale.</hi> By your leave M. Doctor, you forget yourſelfe, for, in an other place o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your booke, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> you <hi>acknowledge,</hi> that M. <hi>Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> writ the ſtory, and he is <hi>one of our principal Authors;</hi> but he ſayes in his relation, (writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten when this ſtory happened) that is was a thing without doubt, becauſe not only M. <hi>Neale,</hi> but other Catholiques <hi>integerrimae fidei, of moſt intire credit,</hi> were eyewitneſſes of Scorys ridiculous manner of conſecrating <hi>Parker,</hi> and the reſt in the Nagshead Taverne. Yet ſuppoſe that M. Neale had bin the only eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe of this action, I ſee nothing that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes more cleerly from ſuch a ſuppoſition, then this concluſion. <hi>Ergo</hi> M. <hi>Neale</hi> muſt needs
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106316:50"/>have bin a perſon of very greate ing enuity, and integrity. Be pleaſed to turne, and frame your interrogations thus. Who believed M. Neale? D. Watſon Bishop of Lincoln. Who believed M. Neale? D. Bluet. Who believed M. Neale? D. Haberley. Who believed M. Neale? All the learned, and vertuous Prieſts, priſoners for their conſcience at <hi>Wisbich.</hi> Who believed M. Neale? All the Catholiques of England. The concluſion is. <hi>Ergo</hi> M. Neale was a man that deſerved great credit, otherwiſe you muſt condemne the greateſt heads amongſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, for believing ſo odd a ſtory, without any credible authority. M. <hi>Neale</hi> had bin a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor in the Vniverſity of Oxford, and forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his chaire, and livelihood, for not taking the oath of ſupremacy: It is incredible that he would feigne ſuch a ſtory as that of the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and therby engage the Catholique Church to practiſe Reordination againſt our knowen Tenets, and his owne conſcience, and by ſuch a relation, declare himſelfe to be not only a virulent backbiter, but an impudent Impoſtor.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But now I muſt prove, that the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ſtory is more then probable, not onely for the quality of the perſons reporting; and believing it, but alſo by the very circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or rather exigences of the time If you looke vpon the Church of England, as it was in the late Kings reigne, it will ſeeme impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that men should chooſe a Taverne for an epiſcopal conſecration: but if we conſider
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106316:51"/>the ſtraight paſſages through which the ſaid Church was forced to march in the beginning of Q. Elizabeths reigne by reaſon of the noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius want it had of Bishops; it will not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſtrange unto vs, that the firſt proteſtant ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendents should go to a Taverne with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to ſupply there the want of their Church, it being well knowne in thoſe days, that neither Scory, nor Hadgkins, nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verdale, were conſecrated Bishops. And though they had the Keyes of the Churches at their command, they had not the <hi>Key of Order,</hi> nor the command of the true Bishops hands, or tongues; therfore it was plotted, that old <hi>Landaffe</hi> should be inveigled to give them a meeting in a Taverne, where with good words, and good cups they hoped to bring the old man to a good humour. But God gave him grace to abſtaine from a ſecond ſcandal, though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had taken the oath of ſupremacy yet in his judgment he was à Catholique, and more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of B. <hi>Bonners</hi> excomunication ready to be fulminated againſt him, then D. <hi>Bramhall</hi> would have his Reader believe. Now, if we will add to this neceſſity the principles, and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the perſons that were to be ordeined Bishops, we shall find there was nothing in the circumſtances of the Taverne conſecration which makes it incredible; for, the perſons were of the opinion then <hi>à la Mode,</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conſecration as a point not neceſſary for Eccleſtical power, though not te be refuſed for publique ſatisfaction, and ſeeing no better
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106316:51"/>could be had, they thought it more expedient to have ſomething preſently, which they might give out for Conſecration, then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect longer for their benefices, which was the buiſnes they were about, and ſought vvith all care, and ſpeed to bring about.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I muſt returne once more to M. <hi>Neale,</hi> and complaine of your railing M. Doctor, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a learned, and honeſt man. You call him a <hi>ſpie, brainſick foole,</hi> &amp;c. and deſpiſe his teſtimony, becauſe he was not ſworne; the credit which as wiſe men as you, did give him, is an argument that he was no foole, and that he could well diſtinguish a Conſecration din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from an ordination; ſuch a miſtake doth not much misbecome a Proteſtant Courtier, as the Earle of Noting ham was; but it can not be believed of ſuch a Prieſt, and a Lector of the Univerſity of Oxford, as M. <hi>Neale.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member when you tooke vpon you in <hi>Bruges</hi> to confirme ſome eminent perſons of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Court, many of the Courtiours were ſtarled at ſo vnuſual a ceremony, as your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation ſeemed to them, and were ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to know what it meant. Why should not the Earle of Notingham be as ignorant of a Proteſtant conſecration, as the Courtiers of <hi>Bruges</hi> were of your ceremonious confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Eſpecially ſeing confirmation should be given to all, and therfore frequent, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fitz. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Britan. Pag.</hi> 317.</note> where as Conſecration of Bishops happens ſeldome.</p>
            <p n="9">9, To M. <hi>Neale,</hi> and other Catholiques eye vvitneſſes of your <hi>Nagshead</hi> conſecration, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106316:52"/>by M. <hi>Conſtable,</hi> may be added the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of all the Puritans. who ſay, <hi>that the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Order, and Ordination of Proteſtant Bishops in England,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina cap.</hi> 8. §. 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 43.</note> had its beginning, and progreſſe in a corner not in a congregation.</hi> I hope the Archio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Chappell of <hi>Lambeth</hi> is no corner; theſe words muſt allude to the <hi>Nagshead</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne (for no other place is heard of but theſe two) and do prove that your Regiſters deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve no credit, but that they were forged in a corner. To the Puritans I will aggregate all your English Clergy in the beginning of K. Iames his reigne, when Holiwood printed, how D. <hi>Alabaſter</hi> asked of M. <hi>Brancroft</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Bishop of London, how his firſt Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents <hi>Parker,</hi> &amp;c. were conſecrated? he answered, that <hi>he hoped, in caſe of neceſsity a Prieſt might ordaine Bishops.</hi> This anſwer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrats the truth of the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory, and the forgery of your Records: becauſe all your Clergy did acquieſce to <hi>Brancroft</hi> anſwer, not one of them had a word to oppoſe againſt F. <hi>Holivvoods</hi> booke, and by their ſilence proved themſelves our witneſſes. <hi>Qui tacet conſentire videtur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Now M. Doctor, that we have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the grounds, circumſtances, and witneſſes of the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory, and of your ſolemne conſecration at Lambeth, let vs compare one with the other, that the Reader may judge, which of both ought to be credited. Our ſtory of the <hi>Nagshead,</hi> is grounded vpon a conſtant tradition of a hundred yeares, betweene wiſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106316:52"/>and ſober perſons; which tradition can not be counterfeited, becauſe no human induſtry can reach, or ſpread ſo farre, as to ſpeake the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thing by ſo different mouthes, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, as there are amongſt our witneſſes, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, Puritans,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> But the ground of your proteſtant conſecration at Lambeth, comes farre short of what yee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to prove by it; for, your ground is your Regiſter, vvhich appeared not (being called for neere a hundred yeares ago) vntill the yeare 1613. And beſides, it might be as eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counterfeited, as any other writing by one, or fewe hands without the concurrence, or conſpiracy of ſo many hands, heads, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite intereſts, as would have bin neceſſary for the counterfeiting of one Tradition. So that as to the grounds of both ſtories, ours is the more credible.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As for circumſtances, which muſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to the place, tyme, and perſons, there is no doubt that our ſtory hath the advantage. The place of your pretended conſecration (Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth) vvas never named (even in your <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novv</hi> Regiſter) vntill 1613. Our ſtory named the <hi>Nagshead</hi> Taverne from the beginning. As for the perſons, their conſcience, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; we have alſo the better; for you have ſeene how litle in thoſe dayes your religion valued Ordination, and your firſt Bishops conſcience could make no ſcruple, to act, and receive in a Taverne, what they judged to be no act of religion. As for the danger of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munires,</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:106316:53"/>or other penalties, they could not feare any; having in their comiſſion an ample diſpenſation to do what they pleaſed againſt the Statutes, and Canons, as hath bin demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in the 2. Chap. And finaly the laſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, which is of time, and perſons, doth ſo divide the relations of your writers, vvho ſpeake of this conſecration at Lambeth, that their contradictions are a ſufficient proofe of your forged records, becauſe relations drawne out of true records can not vary in the names, and nomber of perſons, in the month, or day, which of courſe are expreſſed with great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actnes. You can find no ſuch contradictions in the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But now let vs reflect vpon the number, and quality of the witneſſes. Ours are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly M. <hi>Neale,</hi> but others of <hi>moſt intire credit,</hi> ſpectators of the <hi>Nagthead</hi> Conſecration, as M. <hi>Conſtable</hi> writ in their owne life times, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a hundred yeares ago; but yee never na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any eyewitneſſe but one, the Earle of Notingham, eyther dead when he was cited, or if alive in a manner, and leſſe credible then if he had bin dead. Our eye witneſſes related the ſtory of the Nagshead to D. <hi>Watſon</hi> Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of Lincolns, D. <hi>Bluet,</hi> D. <hi>Haberley,</hi> M. <hi>Conſtable, John Stow,</hi> to the Prieſts priſoners at <hi>Wisbich,</hi> &amp;c. but your one witneſſe never related the ſtory of Lambeth to any that had a name, but only is ſayd by M. <hi>Maſon,</hi> to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve told it to a nameleſſe friend. Our witneſſes published the ſtory of the <hi>Nagshead</hi> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106316:53"/>beginning as ſoone as it happened; but your Witneſſe never published that of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> but told it privatly to a friend, as if forſooth, it had bin a ſecret, or a prejudice to his Church. The teſtimony of our witneſſes agreeth with the principles of your reformation, with the 25. article of your religion, with your tranſlations of ſcripture, with the ſtatuts, 1. and 8. Eliz. 1. and with the confeſſion of <hi>Bancroft,</hi> and the tacite conſent of all your ancient Clergy of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland; and with the publique teſtimony of all the Puritans in print, the teſtimony of your one Witneſſe, and Records, are irreconcilable with the foreſaid evidences. Now judge M. Doctor, who deſerves moſt credit, one yong gallant (in caſe the earle ever shold have ſaid what Maſon pretends) invited to a banket, or many knowing men, eyewitneſſes of the fact? An an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and conſtant tradition of learned, and honeſt men, agreable to your owne principles of religion, to the confeſſion of your owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, ad to the ſtatuts of the land; or a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Regiſter, never cited, nor produced (though earneſtly called for) untill the ſeaſon, and occaſion was paſt; diametricaly oppoſite to your owne articles of faith, and to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of your Church, and to the evidence of your ſtatuts. I hope that neither you, nor any other, will be ſo obſtinate, as hereafter to preferre the relation of an obſcure ſcrole, hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the ſpace of 52. yeares, (the beſt, and greateſt part of the age of your proteſtant Church) be fore the cleere, and publique tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106316:54"/>of ſo many eminent perſons that related, and credited the Nagshead ſtory. But in caſe that you, or any other of your communion, should not be perſwaded by ſo evident reaſons to a truth ſo credible, I muſt attribute your blind obſtinacy to a moſt refined hereſy, which not only depraves the will, and obſcures the underſtanding, but alſo deprives men of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, and makes them walke, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in darkneſſe applauding, and extolling with as greate zeale, and as litle diſcretion, their inviſible Records, as your proteſtant forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did their inviſible Church.</p>
            <p n="13">13. And now M. Doctor, I believe you will pitty the late Kings misfortune, and wish that he had guien <hi>way to the Parliament, to pull doune parliament Bishops,</hi> who had neither hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor divine right to temporal benefices, or ſpiritual offices. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 238.</note> Though it be no pitty <hi>that I was not of his Councell,</hi> its greate pitty that he was not better informed of your Orders; had he bin pleaſed to adviſe, in time vpon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, your ſuperficiall formality had never bin able, to roote out his poſterity, of their well grounded right to three Kindomes. And truly if the Jeſuits Colleges had no more right to the plate of their Churches, and revenues, then yee have to your bishoprickes, and benefices, I <hi>wold not crye out with Ploiden</hi> (as you imagine) <hi>the caſe is altered;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 239.</note> but would perſwade them to reſtitution, and exhort you to the ſame, if this charitable office had not bin prevented by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice, depriving your Clergy of what
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106316:54"/>they ſo wrong fully poſſeſſed. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your miſerable condition, you are pleaſed to ſay, that yee are our feare, and hate. We love your perſons, hate your errours, wonder at your obſtinacy, pardon your former cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and preſent contumelies, pitty your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and much more your blindnes the cauſe of your miſery: neyther enuy your talents, nor feare your power, but continually pray to the Father of mercies, that he may vouchſafe to enlighten your Clergy, and by them open the eyes of others miſled by their errours.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord Audleys teſtification vpon oath of Mortons acknowledging the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ordination in Parliament. The reaſon of beleeving, and publishing the ſaid teſtification, which vpon due examination is much preferred before all others alleadged againſt it.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">1. I Am confirmed in my Lord <hi>Audleys</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of D. <hi>Mortons</hi> ſpeech granting the Nagshead ordination by the very ground you offer to him, and propoſe to others, to make credible a miſtake: For, if my Lord had not bin well aſſured that there is none, he would have willingly layd hold of your courteſy, and of the ſpeech, and perſon of the pretended
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106316:55"/>Bishop of <hi>Lincoln, who,</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>did once mention the fable of the Nagshead in a ſpeech in Parliament, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 26.</note> but with as much deteſtation of it, as your anceſtors vſed to name the Devil. Why might not the miſtake both of the perſon, and of the drift, or ſcope of his ſpeech, be the occaſion of this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> To this interrogation my Lord <hi>Audley</hi> himſelfe will give you an anſwer. But give me leave to aske of you, upon what occaſion could <hi>Lincoln</hi> mention your Nagshead conſecration in a ſpeech in Parliament which might not as well have moved Durham to ſpeake of the ſame? Once you grant ſpeeches of this ſubiect in the vpper houſe, you can hardly free D. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> from having a share in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>But the greatest mistake of all others was</hi> (ſayth the Doctor) <hi>to publish ſuch a notorious untruth to the world, ſo temerariouſly without better adviſe.</hi> I confeſſe that though I never doubted of the truth of my Lord Audleys relation, yet I did foreſee that D. <hi>Morton</hi> would proteſt againſt it, and deny the ſtory, as you do D. <hi>Bancrofts,</hi> concerning the ſame ſubject of the Nagshead. But it is a greate miſtake in you to thinke, that this ſtory of my Lord <hi>Audleyes</hi> was published temerariouſly, and without conſideration and deſigne. For, it was conſidered that either yee would deny it, or grant it. If yee granted D. <hi>Mortons</hi> ſpeech, I had my intent. If yee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it, and produced authentique certificats, and teſtimonies to diſprove what was layd to his charge, your owne certificats, and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique teſtimonies, would be cleer evidences of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106316:55"/>the truth of the Nagshead ſtory, though tkey should vindicate D. <hi>Morton.</hi> For, if the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ſtory had not bin notoriouſly true, and evident in the beginning of Q. Elizabeths reigne, why did not your predeceſſours produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce then authentique Records, or at leaſt ſuch Certificats, as you now do, of your pretended ſolemnity at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> when ſome evidence was deſired of your firſt Bishops to cleere their conſecrations, and the very Regiſters ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly called for? Why did not ſome of your Clergy of thoſe days accuſe D. <hi>Harding</hi> (as you do me) of <hi>calumny, rashneſſe, temerarious cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity</hi> &amp;c. For publishing, and objecting the <hi>Nagshead</hi> ſtory? That yee were vpbraided by him for that ridiculous conſecration, you may ſee in your Bishop <hi>Goodvins</hi> catalogue, whoſe words I cited. Why did they not make the like noyſe when the puritans told them of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their Ordination in a corner, not in a Congregation. Are you more zelous for the honour of one D. <hi>Morton,</hi> then your former Bishops were for their owne credit, and the being of their whole Church? If they had not wanted matter, how could they want minde, or meanes to procure, and publish ſuch teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Lords recorded to be preſent at the ſolemnity of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> as you have got of nine other Lords, members of the late Parliament? could they find no teſtimonies to ſtop the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans clamour? The truth is, the Nagshead ſtory was too well knowne in thoſe dayes to be called in queſtion; and not only then, but even
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106316:56"/>in the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> his reigne, when F. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſc. Lib. de inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiganda Chriſti Eccleſia. Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi> 1603.</note> 
               <hi>Holiwood</hi> objected it in print an. 1603. to all your proteſtant Clergy, and confirmed it by the teſtimony and confeſſion of D. <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft</hi> then living, being actualy in place of Bishop of <hi>London.</hi> Yet no certificats appeared to contradict the ſtory, or <hi>Bancrofs</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, none to convince the Puritans ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection What reaſon could there be of this ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and patience, but cleere evidence of what you now ſo confidently deny? ſo that you ſee M. Doctor, how this ſtir which you have made about <hi>Mortons</hi> vindication, doth prove the truth of your <hi>Nagshead</hi> Conſecration, and that your certificats to diſprove my Lord <hi>Audleys</hi> teſtimony, reflect vpon more then you did deſigne, or deſire, and totaly deſtroy the plea of your forged Regiſters. But let vs heare what he ſaith for himſelfe in his ovvne words.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Having ſeene a booke intituled the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, &amp; Succeſſion of Proteſtant Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, &amp;c. &amp; particularly peruſed that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter calld the Vindication of the Bishop of Durham I finde my ſelf (reflecting of ſome expreſſions therein, &amp; the Bishop of Derry author) obliged to ſay ſomething as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; ſo have deſired place here for a few linies. Who the Author of the treatiſe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faith, &amp;c. fixeth on to prove his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations touching the Bishop of Durhams ſpeech, I know not, for he told me of it befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ever I ſpoke to him, but ſure I am, if it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106316:56"/>be looked after he may have ſufficient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to ſatisfy half a douzen juries; but that which ſtirs me to ſpeake in this matter, is, a note I have at the requeſt of the Bishop of Derry given him vnder my hand, wherein, I ſay in ſubſtance the ſame with the Author touching the Bishop of Durhams ſpeech, as for the booke againſt Epiſcopacy, which was the ground of the diſcourſe, my note only avers it was brought into the howſe, but ſaid not by whome, nor who was the author, in truth I wondered much to finde that the Bishop of Durham doth deny this ſpeech, for I can not remember that ever I heard of, or read the ſtory of the <hi>Nagshead,</hi> till that day in Parlament of my Lord of Durham; then I heard it from him, and this I ſay, as I shall anſweare it before the judgement ſeat of God Allmighty. And I doe not remember that ever I heard the Bishop of Lincolne, or any other Bishop before, or ſince mention the <hi>Nagshead,</hi> or touch that ſtory: if I had, &amp; not named him, my Lord of Durham mought have juſt reaſon to complaine, but my Lord of Derry will not beleeve that I (for I can not but take it to my ſelf) doe, or ever did know the Bishop of Durham, ſo well as to ſweare this was the man. If his Lordship had bin an English Bishop, an fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented Parliaments, he would have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this. Not to multiply vvordes. I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his Lordsp, I could as well, &amp; ſurely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſworen this is the man, the Bishop of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106316:57"/>Durham, as his Lordship could of Sir <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Ratclif</hi> when he lived. Beſides, his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; place of the Bishops bench is too eminent to be miſtaken. An other expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my Lord of Derry is, I do not take my ſelf to be ſo exact Analyſer of a diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, as to be able to take my oath, what vvas the true ſcope of it. Here likevvyſe I muſt beg his Lordships pardon. I knovv no ſuch defect in my ſelf, for there is not any thing more eaſy then to comprehend the true co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of a short a plaine Hiſtoricall diſcourſe as this was; to conclude, as to the Bishop of Durhams denial, I hope that confeſſing him ſelf novv of the age of 95. yeares, it vvill be held no crime to ſay, or impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, to beleeve that one of that grear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, may at leaſt forget, vvhat he ſpake ſo many yeares ſince. For the tvvo cerficats of the other Lords, that of the temporall ſaith litle to my Lord of Derryes purpoſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an indifferent judgment can that of the ſpirituall worke much. For my part, I doe not ſay, that any, or all their Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hips, whoſe names are put to the certificats in the booke, were in the Howſe at this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or if any of them were, that they tooke notice of what my Lord of Durham ſpake, for many diſcourſes are made in Parlaments, &amp; litle notice taken of them, neither had I, of this, but that it was to me a new thing. The Clarque of the Parliament is all ſo brought in to certify, though as to my note
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106316:57"/>his paines mought have bin ſpared, for I doe not mention a booke preſented, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently none to be recorded, and as for ſpeeches, I doe aſſure his Lordship, in the authority of an old Parliament man, that it is not the office of the Clarque to recorde them (his worke would be too great) till it be a reſult or concluſion, &amp; then he writes them downe as Orders, Ordinances, &amp;c. of Parliament. I vvill end this short, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full defence, which I have bin here neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to make for my ſelf vvith many thanks to my Lord of Derry for his charity, &amp; opinion of my ingenuity: &amp; ſeing his Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hips inclination in this matter is to abſolve me from a malicious lye, I vvill abſolve my ſelf as to the miſtakes either in the perſon, or matter, aſſuring his Lordship, &amp; all the vvorld there is none.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Though this relation, and teſtimony gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by my Lord <hi>Audley</hi> doth not only cleere me from caſting any aſpertion vpon D. <hi>Monton,</hi> but alſo makes the whole ſpeeche layd to his charge, ſufficiently credible, (one poſitive witneſſe with ſuch circumſtances proving more then many negative, and it being more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that D. <hi>Morton,</hi> or any other in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, should forget, then my Lord Audley feigne ſuch a ſtory, without any poſſible deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or profit) yet I muſt vindicate my ſelfe from the note of <hi>credulity, rashneſſe, overmuch confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>formal calumly</hi> fixed vpon me by D. <hi>Bramhall,</hi> for believing my Lord, <hi>Audley,</hi> and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106316:58"/>publishing his relation. Is it credulity or rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, good M. Doctor, to believe a perſon of honour, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26.</note> and of ſo greate ingenuity, <hi>as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my Lord Audley to be</hi> and no man of honour can deny in a matter, wherof he had as cleere evidence, and hath as perfect memory, as is poſſible for any man to have of any object, by the acts of his ſenſes, and underſtanding. He proteſteth before God and man, that he never heard any thing of the <hi>Nagshead</hi> conſecration till then, and that the novelty of the ſtory, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de him very attentive; that he remembers the individual circumſtances of the place where D. <hi>Morton</hi> ſtood, his poſture, and all other actions, wherwith he accompanied his ſpeech: and that after D. <hi>Morton</hi> had finished the ſame, he asked a Lord of knowne reputation and wiſedome, whether the firſt proteſtant Bishops had bin ordained in a Taverne? and that he anſwered, the ſtory of the Nagshead was very true.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Now M. Doctor, I beſeech you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how impoſſible it is, that he should be miſtaken, having ſuch aſſurance of his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the evidence of his ſenſes, and underſtanding? Want of memory (the only thing is, or can be objected to make roome for a miſtake in this matter) may occaſion doubts, and perplexities; but not cauſe ſuch poſitive aſſurances, and cleere evidences as my Lord <hi>Audley</hi> to this howre retaines. If it be once granted, that men of judgment may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the evidence they ſweare to have of their owne perfect remembrance, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106316:58"/>concerning an object cleerly acted before their eyes, and diſtinctly convejed into their eares, and particularly reflected vpon, and immediately diſcourſed vpon, you may perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de all the world, that whatſoever they have ſeene, heard, and underſtood, are but dreames, and miſtakes, occaſioned by want of memory. for to impute ſo much dulnes, and ignorance to my Lord of <hi>Audley,</hi> that he could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſcope of a ſpeculation ſo abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſo ſublime, ſo Metaphyſical, as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> ſaying his forefathers were made Bishops in a Tarverne: this were enough to degrade a Doctor of Divinity, and diſpend your epiſcopal pen from its endles, and ſenſles function of ſcribling, if you held theſe titles vpon ſcience, conſcience, or common ſenſe. This is to char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge both the Relator, and Reader with plaine ſtupidity. Muſt men be made out of their wits, becauſe they beare witnes againſt your Clergy? Or can you hope that any man in his wits will heed what you write, when you care ſo little what the Readers judge of you, and your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings?</p>
            <p n="5">5. But here comes a full tide of teſtimonies, to bring him of the ſand he ſtuck himſelf in. Ni ne Peeres have bin ſo vexed with your impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, that they have condeſcended to yield you ſom ſuccour in ſo urgent neceſſity. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>We doe hereby teſtifie, and declare that to the beſt of our preſent knowledge, and remembrance, no ſuch booke againſt Bishops as is there mentioned was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the houſe of Peeres in that Parliament,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106316:59"/>and conſequently that no ſuch ſpeech as is there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended was, or could bo made by him, or any other againſt it.</hi> Jam far from calling in queſtion the ingenuity of theſe honorable perſons, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting unto them the want of incapacity to comprehend the ſcope of what <hi>Morton</hi> then ſaid, or of any thing he ever could have ſaid, if it had any ſcope; but I muſt call your judgment in queſtion for thinking that what yow have got will ſerve your turne. If it doe not its not their fault in giving what you asked, but yours in asking you knew not what. The queſtion is, whether <hi>Morton</hi> acknowledged in parliament the <hi>Nagshead</hi> merry meeting; but whether it were vpon occaſion of a booke publickly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, or privatly delivered, whether dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the parliament, or diſtributed amongſt the members of Parlement, whether in this man, or that mans name, whether Lord, or not Lord, what imports it to the matter in hand? There are none of theſe Lords, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or doubt, but that many by-ſpeeches have bin made by Bishops in Parliament vpon leſſer occaſions, then theſe J rehearſed, and perhaps ſome with no occaſion, and alſo to no purpoſe at all, unles the reſt have bin more carefull in ſpeaking then you in printing. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 10.</note> You confeſſe a booke to have bin <hi>dedicated</hi> to the Parliament againſt Epiſcopacy, and the booke to have bin writ by a Lord; you confeſſe <hi>to have heard that the B. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 26.</note> of Lincolne did once mention the fable of the Nagshead in a ſpeech in Parliament,</hi> and you will not deny, but that Durham for his many
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106316:59"/>writings, and great age might have bin as fit, and forward to talke as another, and if you looke but upon the text of the teſtimony, you have begged, you find not a word that argues, or intimats his not having avowed the Nags<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ordination. They only ſay they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>no ſuch booke,</hi> to wit with all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances mentioned, and conſequently no ſpeech <hi>againſt it.</hi> They may remember a ſpeech vpon occaſion of a booke, wherin Durham took harbour in the <hi>Nagshead</hi> Tarverne, and yet ſay with truth they do not remember that ſpeech, or any other to have bin made againſt ſuch a booke ſigned with all thoſe individual particularities. And further there might have bin ſuch a ſpeech, and ſuch a booke, and ſuch circumſtances: and yet they might have forgot them all, or in part, after ſo many years; but I need not this, for they do not deny to remember the ſpeech, nor the booke, nor any circumſtance belonging to the point, we diſpute. And I marke their atteſtation to be couched in termes ſo preciſe, and cautious, as both to content you, who preſume to make any thing ſerve your purpoſe, and yet ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to contradict, nor wholy conceale the truth. For, thoſe that with ſo carefull attention tyed their atteſtation ſo faſt to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial part of the buiſnes, knew full well that the attentive Reader would therby percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve they could have ſaid more of the ſubſtance, if they had not bin by themſelves, or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers perſuaded that it was not convenient to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106316:60"/>publish all they remembred. But your adding the Clark of the Parliaments teſtimony is a meere childish ſimplicity, what ſayth he? <hi>I do not find any ſuch booke preſented, nor any entery of any ſuch ſpeech made by B. Morton.</hi> Will you make men beleeve that every ſpeech is ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or that if juſt ſuch a booke was not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally preſented, that the ſpeech was not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vpon occaſion of a booke, or that a booke in good English may not be ſaid to be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, although it be not delivered in ſuch ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as requires the putting it vpon record? It is much want that brought you doune to ſuch beggarly shifts, to go from dore to dore begging atteſtations about an inconſiderable circumſtance, and make ſoo poore, and pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of what you have ſcraped together. You forget to beg the favour of your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to let you talke diſparatas in this deſperat caſe, and beg pardon of your Reader for abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and preſuming that he is void of common ſenſe, and no leſſ reaſon you have to beg pardon of your partners for your want of ability, or Perhaps fidelity in the defence of the common cauſe. If you were a lawyer by profeſſion, as you profeſſe here much skill to litle purpoſe in law matters, I beleeve after ſuch pleading as this, you would get few clients, and ſmal fees.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Put the caſe your Brother <hi>Durham</hi> had bin accuſed of treaſon, and you were allowed to plead for him (which equity in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries is not denied) now there coms in a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106316:60"/>whoſe ingenuity you grant, and no man can deny, he takes vpon his oath, as he hopes to be ſaved, that he heard the ſaid <hi>Durham</hi> vpon occaſion of a ſedicious pamphlet, make a ſpeech to the people, wherin he exhorted them to deliver vp a towne to the enemy; that he knowes the man accuſed as vvell as you knew Sir <hi>George Ratcliffe;</hi> that he remembers cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the very place, and poſture, wherin he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſpeech, and further more that the ſpeech was ſo vnexpected, that it made him in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular manner attentive, that immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he diſcourſed vpon it with an other, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelf better of the ground of that ſpeech, and all this he proteſts over, and over agine in all occaſions offered, as he is to ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in the day of judgment. Put the caſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he should ſay that he thinks the pamphlet was writ by ſuch a man, or given in ſuch a mans name, and that it was preſented by one, that made a leg as he gave it, and delivered it with his right hand; but of theſe petty circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he gives no aſſurance vnder his hand, as being things he made no very particular account of, or reflexion vpon. Now enters M. <hi>Bramhall</hi> the lawyer puft vp vvith preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption that he can talke all the world out of their wits, and ſenſes, Firſt bragging, and vapouring, and threatening no leſſe then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing demonſtrations, then vpbraiding his adverſary with credulity, temerity for taking notice of ſuch a teſtimony, and forewarning him with a moſt paſſionate zeale of his credit,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106316:61"/>hereafter to turne ſtoick with <hi>Epictetus,</hi> and learne to diſtruſt, and having wearied himſelf, and others with theſe Preambular imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences, and diſpoſed all by his preſumption, and paſſion not to beleeve a word he shall ſay, atlength he coms cloſe to the point, and tels the judge, that the witneſſe doth not take himſelf for ſo exact <hi>Analyſer</hi> of a diſcourſe, as to vnderſtand what is meant by theſe words, <hi>to deliver a tovvne to the enemy,</hi> and if this be not ſufficient to cleere the matter, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a writing wherin ſome perſons ſay noe more, but that they doe not remember after 17. or 18. yeares ſuch a Pamphlet, that is writ by ſuch a man, and delivered with that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and in ſuch a mans name, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no ſpeech to have bin made againſt it, as is pretended, and that it was not in ſuch manner preſented, as thoſe are, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in publicke Regiſters, but as to the effect of the ſpeech not ſo much as a negative teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, not ſo much as a word ſignifying it to be not remembred, but rather the contrary: otherwiſe they had ſpoken home to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and not confined their oblivion within a few circumſtances, and thoſe nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to what is in queſtion. But if the ſaid lawyer should not ſo much as prove that the witneſſes produced by him were preſent at the foreſaid ſpeech, nor give any reaſon, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture why they ſaid nothing towards the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of the ſpeech it ſelf, in caſe they had bin preſent, but only of their having forgot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106316:61"/>accidental ſuperflous particularities, not regarded, or formally avouched by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary witnes; nor alleadge any Lavv, Cuſtom, preſident, or argument, why ſuch a negative teſtimony of the not remembrance of inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable circumſtances should prevaile againſt the plaine, cleere, poſitive, vndoubted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of a witnes beyond all exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion: and further should preſſe his adverſary ever, and an on to legal proofes, and admit of no others, and yet himſelf inſiſt chiefely vpon a proof againſt the law of all nations that have law, to wit vpon the denial of the perſon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, and others equally concerned; if, I ſay, a Lawyer should plead in this manner, would any judge, or any man of judgment cleere the Delinquent of treaſon, or the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate of treacherous prevarication, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant preſumption vpon ſo frivolous, and idle diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And yet this is your caſe, M. Doctor, this, I ſay, or worſe then this; for beſides your il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal plea of producing <hi>Morton</hi> as a witnes in his owne cauſe oppoſing a negative teſtimony againſt a poſitive; and that of the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, this of ſubſtance, and his fellow Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents as much concerned in this matter as himſelf, who, if this ſtory be confeſſed, have no more character, or order, then a Brovvniſt Miniſter, or <hi>Tubpreacher,</hi> yet there is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial exception againſt the perſon of <hi>Morton,</hi> as having bin often, and evidently convicted of moſt plaine wilfull, vn excuſable lies, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106316:62"/>impoſtures in his ſeverall writings concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Religion, which shamefull abominable practiſe he hath vſed when he was leſſ concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then in this preſent occaſion. Whether I ſpeake with reaſon, or paſſion the Reader will shortly judge of himſelf, and with all what exception may be taken againſt his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues. I shall give neyther him, or you any names though provoked by both, he calls me <hi>an impudent libeller,</hi> you call M. <hi>Neale a brai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſicke foole.</hi> I know you are both as vvell ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Civility, as Divinity, and need not to take you for my Maiſters, or Paternes. But I shall teach the Reader to frame a right no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of you, and your tribe, and remit the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you names to his diſcretion.</p>
            <p>As to the Noblemen you cited, I have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined their atteſtation with that regard, as neyther to give offence to them, nor advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to you, nor prejudice to the truth. To whom I make bold to preſent this humble petition that they will be pleaſed in their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to conſider the difference betwixt theſe two conſequences, which without any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall Logique is eaſily diſcerned.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The firſt. I remember cleerly, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to have heard ſuch a ſpeech, which the attention to it, the admiration of it, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion vpon it hath deeply imprinted in my memory, therfore I may ſecurely ſay, and ſweare ſuch a ſpeech y have heard. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. I doe not remember after 17. or 18. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res certaine occaſional circumſtances of ſuch a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106316:62"/>ſpeech, or perhaps not the ſpeech it ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I might have bin abſent, or not atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to it, or made litle account of it. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another mans perfect remembrance is not to be credited. Although the Roman Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour <hi>Hortenſius</hi> is renowned for his prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious memory, yet I could never heare any thing of him which might give occaſion to thinke that if he had forget ſomthing belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a ſpeech made in the ſenate 17. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res before, that his oblivion would have bin thought ſufficient to voyd the evidence of it drawne from the ſolemne oath, and perfect remonſtrance of a lawfull witnes. And albeit <hi>Mithridates</hi> could give account of every ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers name in his army, yet if one had bin proved by the oath of a perſon of honour to have ſerved him in his warres, can any man imagin the King would have diſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed his ſervice, becauſe after 17 yeares he, or ſome others had forgot his name? Not many yeares ſince there appeared a dim Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met obſerved by fevv, yet I could never find any that hath pervſed their ohſervations ſo mad, as to call it in queſtion, becauſe he or ſome others can not call to memory the ſight of it, notwithſtanding a perfect remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce they might have had of their being abroad that very night it is ſaid to have bin ſeen by others.</p>
            <p n="9">9. But you M. Doctor, advance not ſo far as to evince the preſence of your witneſſes, much leſſ their ſpeciall attention, reflexion,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106316:63"/>admiration, or the like, which are the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of a laſting memory, for my witnes doth not mention the day. Wherefore it was a worke not only of ſupererogation, but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, that your ſuperintending Brethren should put in their atteſtation, that they ſate in the Parliament begun at Wesminſter the 3. day of Novemb. 1640. without giving ſome ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of their ſitting, or ſtanding in Parliament the time of the ſpeech. Yet <hi>Mortons</hi> atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not only ſuperflous, but ridiculous. A man that hath bin publickely, manifeſtly, and frequently convicted of moſt wilfull, and moſt impudent lyes in his writings, is grovvne ſo forgetfull not only of what he ſpoke, but of what any man in his wits ought to ſpeake, that he delivers himſelf in theſe terms. <hi>I could never have made ſuch a ſpeech as is there preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> (and the proofe it excellent) <hi>ſeeing y have ever ſpoken according to my thoughts, and alvvays believed that fable of the Nagshead conſecration to have proceeded from the father of lyes.</hi> A deafe man might as well ſay, he heard it with his heeles, as that <hi>Morton</hi> should ſay he ſpoke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his thoughts, when he thought it convenient to ſpeake otherwiſe. And no leſſe ridiculous induſtry was vſed in procuring a publique Notary, and five witneſſes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke men believe that the atteſtation is truly his owne, not falsly fathered vpon him, for no body doubted but he would give a moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teſtimony for himſelf, and his cauſe, but no man that knowes him by his writings vvill
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106316:63"/>give credit to any thing he ſayeth in behalfe of religion. Perſuade the old man that you have found a new trick to make better vſe of of the <hi>Nagshead</hi> conſecration, then that of Lambeth, you shall have him, with double number of witneſſes avow the ſpeech, he hath diſavowed. For is it credible he feares a fevv private mens ſilent cenſure, who hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his face againſt the publicke reproach of as many ſchollers as read bookes of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy? But I shall preſent him, and his fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes to your eyes, in their owne glaſſe, that you may know them better by ſight then by hearſay.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:106316:64"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the wilfull, and shamefull falſifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and falſities of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>I require no gentle, and courteous, nor ſo much as unpartial, and unpaſſionate readers, I am content with any partiality, or paſſion, provided that it doe not wholy deprive them of the uſe of their eyes, and reaſon. I give but a ſcantling, and that in haſt, and out of ſuch bookes I had at hand, and what I found with litle ſeeking. I am ſo aſſured by my owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the plenty of this kinde of ware, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly to be found in the prime Proteſtant writers, particularly in the English Nation, that I fear no other reproach, but of my ſparing paines in collecting no greater heapes of this abominable filth, to cauſe therby a wholſom, though noyſom deteſtation of that Religion, which is vpheld by ſo vnchriſtian, vnhumane, Diabolical Policy. I begin with <hi>Morton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a virulent, and calumnious pamphlet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled. <hi>A diſcovery of Romish doctrinein caſe of conſpiracy, and rebellion</hi> pag. 4. he alleageth as an ancient decree out of Gracian. Cauſa 15. qu. 6. c. 40. <hi>Si juravi me ſoluturum alicui pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam qui excommunicatur, non teneor ei ſolvere:</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:106316:64"/>firſt it is no decree either of Pope, or Councel, but only words of the gloſſe; ſecondly it is an objection, not the reſolution of the gloſſe, for it reſolves that he is bound to pay, and proves it by divers lawes, and reaſons.</p>
            <p>In his treatiſe called <hi>a confutation of the Popes ſupremacy, as ſupreame head of rebellion pag.</hi> 2. He affirmeth that in the old teſtament the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits are forced to allow that the king was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame head of the Church in ſpirituall affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and ordering Prieſts, and for proofe citeth Salmeran. d. 12. in ep. Pauli in gen. §. ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Where he doth not only cleerly hold, but largly prove the quite contrary, and ſolves the objections, and further ads that in caſe it had bin ſo in the old, it doth not follow that it is ſo in the new.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>reply, and full ſatisfaction concerning the charge againſt Proteſtants for rebellion</hi> &amp;c. pag. 3. he imputeth to <hi>Vaſques,</hi> that he holds a man may be an heretique though he be not obſtinate, wheras in the very diſputation men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; Vaſques guieth this definition of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, commonly received. <hi>Haereſis nihil eſt aliud,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſp.</hi> 126. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> quam error in rebus fidei cum partinacia,</hi> and it is impoſſible that <hi>Morton</hi> should have bin igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this notion of hereſy, ſo frequently taught, and generally received, and by Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques expreſſely.</p>
            <p>In the ſame booke pag. 38. <hi>Morton</hi> feigneth that divers Catholique authors hold <hi>that Popes cannot poſſibly be heretiques as Popes, now for the concluſion, and conſequently cannot be depoſed,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:106316:65"/>among theſe, he brings <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> though Bellarmin directly teach that the Pope may be an heretique, and therupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Church, or rather <hi>is ipſo facto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,</hi> and may be ſo declared by the Church, and citeth the very canon of Gracian, ſaying <hi>haereticum Papam poſſe judicari, expreſsè habetur Can. ſi Papa</hi> diſt. 40. <hi>Morton</hi> citeth <hi>Azor</hi> for the ſame l. 5. c. 14. &amp; <hi>Valentia</hi> analy: l. 8. c. 3. and <hi>Salmeron.</hi> Cam. in Galat: 2. d. 24. and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> de locis l. 6. cap. 8. and <hi>Stapleton doctrin.</hi> l. 6. initio. And Coſterus de Pontif. in Ench. c. 3. and yet all theſe in the very places teach plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and flatly the very contrary. And further he is not ashamed to ad that theſe authors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their doctrin by the univerſall conſent of Romish Devines, and Canoniſts for the ſpace of 100. yeares, whereas they boath teache the contrary, to wit, that the Pope may be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and depoſed, and innumerable others of that age, true it is that God neyther hath, nor will permit, that any Pope, though here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique in his private opinion should by publique decree <hi>ex cathedrâ</hi> define any hereſy, neither, for any thing wee know out of hiſtory well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, can it be convinced that any Pope hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath bin an heretique in his private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, albeit in this point there be different opinions, which nothing at all belong to the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But I muſt invite the reader, at leaſt for a pleaſant entertainment, if no higher motive can induce him, to peruſe <hi>Mortons</hi> diſcourſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106316:65"/>againſt Aequivocation, and confer it with the anſwer contained in a booke intituled <hi>A treatiſe tending to Mitigation,</hi> it will be no ſmale ſporte, I do not ſay, to catch him nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in ignorant miſtakes, but to heare rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping loud lies one after an other, in that very booke where he deteſteth Aequivocation, and profeſſeth a moſt religious preciſenes in point of truth. For example, he citeth Azor. l. 11. inſtit. cap. 4. quite contrary to this meaning, patching words to geather, that were ſpoken ſeperatly, and to an other end, and falſly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in to English that very text of Azor. which himſelf citeth in the margen. The words in latin are, <hi>Si venit ex loco aliquo peſte minimè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto, qui falsò habetur pro infecto.</hi> Which Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton turnes thus into English, <hi>if he com from a place infected.</hi> But truely tranſlated make the caſe wholy different, and are theſe, <hi>if he came from a place not infected, which falſely is held to be infected.</hi> But he is not only content to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of vnexcuſable falsehood by men that ſtudy moraliſts, but even by ſchoolboys, that read Tullies offices, in his 90. page he doth ſo groſſely pervert the ſenſe, change the words, and diſtroy the whole drift of Tullies diſcourſe l. 3. offic. §. <hi>Regulus</hi> and §. <hi>ſed ſi,</hi> that it is a wonder to ſee what impudenſy growes from a cuſtom of lying. Theſe are but a few examples of the many detected by the aforeſaid Treatiſe of Mitigation, and an other called <hi>A quiet, and ſober reckoning with Thomas Morton</hi> by the reading wherof, and conferring each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106316:66"/>with the bookes cited every one may in a short time, and no great trouble judge by his eyes whether I have reaſon to except againſt ſuch a witnes in his owne cauſe, and what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there is to follow ſo wilfully, and wickedly blind leaders.</p>
            <p>But I cannot but wonder at one circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that after <hi>Morton</hi> had gained reputation by this practiſe, he was promoted to the title and profits of a Bishopricke, purchaſing by a new kind of fimony, not with buying, but with lyeing, a rich benefice. I <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> or <hi>Perron</hi> could have bin convicted of this falſe, and baſe proceeding either before, or after their Cardinals caps, what a noyſe would have bin, when we heare ſuch a clamour, vpon that which is not proved, but only pretended to be a credulous miſtake? Yet when I conſider <hi>John Foxes</hi> Acts, and Monuments, the very Magazin of no leſſe malicious, then ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous lies, to have got ſo honorable a place in Proteſtant Churches, and that not by vulgar ſimplicity, but by publick authority, not by connivence, or negligence, but vpon deſigne, and by command: when I ſee this abomination hath ſtood ſo long in the holy place, I wonder no more at <hi>Mortons</hi> promotion, nor at whole Nations deceaved by <hi>Mahomets Alcoran.</hi> If I should inſiſt vpon the number of thoſe, that by commaund, or concurrence are guilty of the falſehood of Foxes booke, I should accuſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, then I am by this preſent occaſion obliged; but the Miniſters I cannot excuſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106316:66"/>vpon any title, for although they be of meane learning, and no extraordinary reading, yet the falſities are ſo numerous, and obvious, that it is impoſſible but many should have fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obſervation of moſt. And by the booke of the three Converſions of England, and the Examen of Foxes Calender, which have bin printed almoſt threeſcore yeares ſince; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve come to the hands of many Proteſtant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, this Foxes fowle worke hath bin ſo plainly diſcovered, that thoſe, who have ſeen it, if they had leaſt zeale, or love, or care of truth, ought to have informed their Brethren, and not to have permitted any Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to be longer prophaned with ſo publick a ſlaunder, and shame of Chriſtianity. Should a renegate Captive tell his maiſter, that the ſect amongſt Chriſtians, which he had bin taught, was maintained by ſuch falſe, and shamfull practiſes, he would eaſily gaine Credit of a true Proſelite turned Turke vpon conſcience, and not convenience. I need not ſet downe <hi>Foxes</hi> impoſtures, for you shall ſee them in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid bookes ſo groſſe, and thick ſet one by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that it will be harder to make a way through them, then find the way to them. I will paſſe my word the Author does him no wrong, and the reader vpon his owne examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will take my word in an other occaſion.</p>
            <p>But to returne to <hi>Morton</hi> now with a white Rochet on his backe, but with as little inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, and candour of mind as before. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of thoſe unhallowed hands hath not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106316:67"/>imprinted the leaſt marke of grace in his ſoule, or shame in his forehead. In the grand impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture writ by him then B. of Cov. and Lichf. pag. 85. edit. 2. he ſets doune a large, and lying deſcription of the Inquiſitions cruelty, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, <hi>So your Authour.</hi> And who do you thinke is this Author, but <hi>Cornellius Agrippa</hi> a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, as himſelf confeſſeth of himſelfe? And where doth he write what heer is alleaged againſt vs? In a booke condemned by our Church. Not a word of theſe circumſtances; but only that he is our Author, to make the Reader believe he is one we have no reaſon to except againſt. You had better take him to your ſelfe: for his blacke art is of the ſame colour with yours, and taught by one maiſter, who eſteems you the better ſcholler, having done more miſchiefe with your falſe jugling, then Agrippa with his conjuring. Now pag. 388. the ſame jugling trick over againe. Marke the enſuing words. <hi>Els why is it that your owne Thua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſpeaking of this ſeparation</hi> (Viz of Luther) <hi>ſayd that ſome in thoſe days layd the fault vpon the Pope Leo? More fully your Caſſander, an Author ſelected in thoſe days by the King of the Romans, as the chiefeſt divine of his.</hi> And pag. 385. He cals Thuanus <hi>our noble Historian.</hi> Who knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Thuanus but by this mans relation, would take him to be, not only a ſound unſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Catholique, but of ſpecial regard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: wheras both our common opinion, and his owne Annals prove him a Hugonot. But beſides falſely reporting him for a Catholic, he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106316:67"/>is plainly falſified in theſe very places alleaged. In the firſt he ſpeaks not of Luthers ſeparation, but of the election of Prelats in France; and in the 2. where he ſpeaks of benefices, <hi>Morton</hi> makes him ſpeake of Indulgences, in both pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces evidently againſt his cleere words, which read as they ſtand in <hi>Thuanus</hi> have not the leaſt shadow of ambiguity. But the makeing <hi>Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> ours, and our chiefeſt Devine being liſted in our Index of forfidden bookes amongſt the Heretiques of the firſt ranke, and his owne writings accuſing him, not only of the general hereſies of theſe times, but of others alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to himſelf, is not only a shamles, but ſenſeles impoſture. It is a labour too loathſom to dig any longer in this filthy dunghil of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. And it is a madnes in any man that already knowes <hi>Morton</hi> by his notoriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent lying bookes, or before he take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him vpon this admonition to give the leſt credit to any thing he shal ſay, write, ſigne, or ſweare concerning Religion, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed by his owne writings to have loſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of conſcience, all feare of reproach from men, or punishment from God. Did he believe there is a God who hath prepared a Hel of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for thoſe, who maintaine a diviſion in the Church by ſo many wilfull impoſtures, and ſeriouſly intended to prevent the ſcourge of his heavy hand, could he ſtand gazing vpon his grave at ſo nigh a diſtance without repenting, or can he truly repent without recanting. Be not amazed that he remains without feeling,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106316:68"/>for, no <hi>Pharaos,</hi> no <hi>Anthiochus</hi> pride, and cruelty doth ſo harden the hart of a Reprobate as a long cuſtome of denving, and belying the known truth, which <hi>Morton</hi> hath done for many yeares. For, albeit his blindnes were ſo great as not to ſee the manifeſt truth of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet impoſſible it is, he should not ſee the falſe calumnies, falſe tranſlations, and falſe allegations he bringeth againſt our Authors, whome he hath read with his owne eyes. Let any man marke his manner of perverting them, he shall cleerly perceave that it could not be ſo done without haveing ſeene the very places, and read them at leaſure.</p>
            <p>But this hath bin the continual practiſe of defenders of hereſy in all ages, and in this laſt age, and in English writers, and in the moſt eminent of them moſt conſpicuous. Let the reader, who deſirs to be ſatisfied in this point, procure, as he may eaſily, the forenamed trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe tending to mitigation, where in the 12. chap. he shall find the prime Proteſtant writers in the begining of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> reigne, and in the firſt place <hi>Jewel</hi> called B. of Salisb. guilty of moſt enormous, unexcuſable untruths. He shal heare this impudent Miniſter braging, and braving that we cannot alleadge <hi>one Author, one Doctor, one ſentence, no not two lines</hi> in behalf of any one of the 28. articles he attributeth to vs, wherin are contained the real preſence, private Maſſe, images, the Popes primacy, offering vp of Chriſt in ſacrifice, common prayer in a ſtrange language &amp;c. Whether we have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106316:68"/>authority for theſe Tenets is not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent queſtion; but whether we cannot find one ancient Doctor, or two lines in favor of any one oft them. He shall heare him cite S. Auſtin as allowing mariage after vowes made of chaſtity in his booke <hi>de Bono viduitatis</hi> the drift of which booke being wholy, and plainly to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. He shal heare him cry downe another S. Auſtin the Apoſtle of Engl. not only againſt the authority of ancient Hiſtory, but even againſt the confeſſion of <hi>John Foxes Acts, and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> He shal heare ſo much, that he will not need to goe further to Seeke <hi>Harding,</hi> and others, who have at large diſcovered the falſe luſtre of this counterfeit <hi>Jewel,</hi> this pretious ſtone layd in the fundation of the English Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon. He shal find the like falſe dealing of <hi>Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shill, Clarke,</hi> and <hi>Perkins.</hi> As for John Foxe the Reader after a short taſt of his knavery is remitted to the third part of the three conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Engl. where in one chap. are ſett downe ſeverally above a hundred and twenty wilfull lyes, vttered by <hi>Foxe</hi> in leſs then three leaves of his Acts, and Monuments, and thoſe ſuch, as no ways may be excuſed, eyther by ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, or error; but muſt needs proceed from vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary fraud, and malice, himſelf knowing that it was falſe, which he related. I omit what is further alleadged of malicious fraud in the writings of Sir <hi>Francis Haſtings,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edoard Cooke,</hi> but a word I muſt ad of Sir <hi>Philip Pleſſis Mornay</hi> a frenchman, to shew that it is not a national inclination of the English, but of any
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106316:69"/>nation infected with hereſy to maintaine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical errours with voluntary falshood. The french Janſeniſts of late make good my aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this french Calviniſt will make it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In a booke of his full of authorities againſt the Maſſe, he was charged by Peron, then B. of <hi>Eureux,</hi> after Cardinal, with five hundred wilfull falſifications, and vpon ſuite made to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth by the ſaid <hi>Peron</hi> it came to a publick trial in preſence of the King of France, and great part of his Nobility on the 4. of May 1600. Of theſe five hundred were exhibited threeſcore to <hi>Pleſſis</hi> to take his choiſe for the firſt dayes tryall, who tooke nineteene of thoſe, which he thought himſelf beſt able to excuſe. Now the ſtraitnes of time permitting only nine to be examined, he was both by his owne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Judges, and the Catholick Judges on the other ſide condemned of falſification, and untrue dealing in all nine, after he had bin per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſay what he could in his defence. And <hi>Peron</hi> further preſſed him to returne to the like trial of the reſt of the five hundred, but <hi>Pleſſis</hi> could not be brought to it. This publique trial is largely related, and defended in the end of the firſt tome of the 3. part of the three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of England, and appeares in the Kings owne letter in print, as alſo by the publick Acts ſet forth by the approbation of the ſaid King and his counſel.</p>
            <p>If I should proceed on with the vnchriſtian, and vnhuman proceeding of our English Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in their shamfull calumniations, and falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106316:69"/>it wold be an endles worke. I shall remit the reader to a booke intituled a ſearch made into matters of Religion by <hi>Francis Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham</hi> Deacon of the Proteſtant Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his change to the Catholick, where he may find ſuch foule dealing of ſo many English Proteſtant Miniſters, <hi>Bel, Doves, Jewel, Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clif</hi> &amp;c. that with conferring the praces by his owne induſtry he will never need to informe himſelf more by the relations of others. Let him but read the Diſcuſſion of D. <hi>Barlows</hi> anſwer togeather with the ſupleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and adjoynder, he shall know the lying ſpirit of <hi>Barlow, Reynolds, Dunnes,</hi> and <hi>Andrewes,</hi> and this mans not only falfities, but follies in his anſwer to Card. <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Apollogy. <hi>Infelix puer, atque impar Achilli.</hi> I cannot conceave what excuſe a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant that hath any ſenſe of Religion can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge why he should not endeavour to rectify his judgment vpon ſo eaſy conditions. The bookes are not hard to be got, the places are eaſy to be found, and examined; there is no more exacted of him, but to beleeve what he ſees. And in caſe he be a Proteſtant of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne prelatique fashion, who by an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency to any Religion whereunto the Apoſtles short Creed admitted by <hi>Arrians, Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Neſtorians, Eutichians, Pelagians,</hi> may be applyed, hath little, or no regard of any Religion at all; yet to ſatisfy himſelf in point of curioſity, or Policy concerning Religion, methinks he should be deſirous to try by his own experience whether men by facing about
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106316:70"/>with inconſtancy of enterchanging opinions, and facing it out with impudency of manifeſt lies, and calumnies may build, and vphold an imaginary Church in the fancies of ignorant, and careles peeple. I can aſſure him that he shall diſcover in the practiſe of Proteſtant wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters more admirable effects of knavery, then in the precepts and preſidents of his only admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and adored Apoſtle <hi>Machiavel.</hi> He will prefer English men in this point of wit, which he eſteems the higheſt, before the Italians; for Machiavel, the ſole Italian, he admires could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make ſuch reſolutions in Italy, although it was the marke he aimed at, as English Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have made in England. Vnles it were not the want of wit in the Miniſter, but the too much wit of the ſchollers. Perhaps <hi>Machiavel</hi> durſt not preſume to find peeple in his countrey apt to beleeve, that of a number of Popes for many ages could be forged one monſtrous man called Antichriſt. He could not imagine that Italians would kill one another in good earneſt, vpon hopes to deſtroy this imaginary Monſter: nor that Tinkers, and Coblers brains could be ſo far paſt mending, that they would be caſt into the fire in defence of the fond inventions of a fewlewd, and lying Apoſtatas: or that the folly of theſe brainſike Idiots would ſerve for a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to men in their wits. <hi>Machiavel</hi> had read as much hiſtory, as <hi>John Foxe,</hi> or his Dutch Maiſters the Magdeburgeans, and could have made Acts, and Monuments with as many fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and fewer follies; yet he had a better
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106316:70"/>conceit of his Nation, then to hope that ſuch a booke should be placed in Churches by publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke authority, and ſtand ſo long by the shamles malice of ſome, and careles ſtupidity of others. He knew his countrymen had ſeene many pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ancient Architecture, that they would not be eaſily perſuaded to pray with ſecurity in a Chappel ſupported by ſuch a pillar. They had heard ſo much of the Buls ſacrificed to <hi>Jupiter Capitolinus,</hi> that it would be hard to make them beleeve that the praying before the Picture of Chriſt was in effect the old Idolatry of the Romans. The Croſſes, and Images they had ſeen in the grots of the ancient Martyrs, freed them from the ſuſpicion of ſuperſtitious No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. <hi>Machiavel</hi> knew better then Miniſters the vices, and abuſes of the Roman Clergy, and deſired no leſſe to decry, and deſtroy it; yet he was far from expecting, that Carters, and Catchpols, Porters, and Pedlers would be heard with patience in Italy prate Non-ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce out of pulpits, and take vpon them to refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and pull downe Pope and Prelates; and much leſſe that the ſucceſſours of theſe should be reſpected as prieſts meerly by their wearing long coats without any evidence produced of their vocation, conſecration, and Juriſdiction, beſides what they received from a woeman diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with the very <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of the Conſecraters beyond all that hath bin pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, or pretended by the Vicar of Chriſt. He could not ſuſpect that wary and jealous Italians would confeſſe their hidden ſins to men who
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106316:71"/>had no other key of power, nor locke of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but of a Woemans making. <hi>Machiavel</hi> could have forged a new Bible with falſe tranſlations, and knew fullwell that deſtruction is cauſed by Diviſion, and no better way to divide Religion in to innumerable ſects then to make every mans fond faney the Judge of a falſified Rule of Religion, he had got what he ſought and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſenſes of Gods word had abolished all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of God, and goodnes, had he thought that Italian Bibles would doe what the English ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve done, but being by office a Secretary, he was afraid to be proved a notorious falſary. He knew that by abuſing ſcripture as our English trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters have done both he and all thoſe, who should conſpire with him would forfeit their credit, and become infamous after ſo many, ſo groſſe, ſo palpable diſcoveryes of their falſe dealing. I shal note a few, and direct the Reader for many more to be found in <hi>Gregory Martins</hi> diſcovery of the manifold corruptions of holy ſcriptures by the Heretiques of our dayes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the English Sectaries.</p>
            <p>In the Bible of the yeare 1562. cloſſe vpon the time of the pretended ſolemne, and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Conſecration at <hi>Lambeth</hi> by impoſition of hands, and other things requiſite they make the Scripture ſpeake in thoſe termes Act. 14. v. 23. <hi>When they had ordained Elders by Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in every Congregation,</hi> and the ſame words are kept ſaving the Change of Congregation into <hi>Church</hi> in the Bible 1628. vpon this place I have two things to note firſt the wreſting of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106316:71"/>word <hi>Chirotonia</hi> from the Eccleſiaſtical to the profane ſenſe of election by ſtretching forth the hand according to the uſe of the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens, and againſt the interpretation of S <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> who in cap. 58. Iſai. interprets <hi>Chirotonia, Clericorum ordinatio,</hi> not <hi>Electio;</hi> and againſt S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. Tim. 5. v. 22. where ſpeaking of ordination he ſaith, lay hands ſuddainely on noe man. The ſecond, that both in thoſe firſt times, and alſo in theſe later they declared by their verſion of Scripture their opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning orders by election, and not by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, which includes impoſition of hands. Now you shal ſee how the Scripture is made to ſpeake to the tune of the Princes humour, notwithſtanding they preach ſo lowd that all men, both Kings, and Popes muſt be put in tune by the ſound of the letter. During King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt his reigne, the onely tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this place 1. Petr. 2. v. 13. which in the original Greeke is <hi>ſubmit yourſelves vnto every humane creature for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as excelling, or,</hi> &amp;c. was then <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves vnto all manner ordinauce of man whether it be to the King, as into the chiefe head, or,</hi> &amp;c. But vnder Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> who, as <hi>Cambden</hi> in her liſe relateth, would not be called head of the Church, but ſupreme gouvernor, <hi>To the King as having preheminence</hi> Bible 1577. and <hi>To the King as ſuperior</hi> Bible 1579. But in King Iames his time, who preſſed much the oath of ſupremacy. <hi>To the King as ſupreme</hi> Bibles 1012. 1618. Doe you not ſee theſe fawning
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106316:72"/>Paraſites make ſport vvith the Scripture to pleaſe their Princes?</p>
            <p>Whilſt liberty was cried downe where they should have put <hi>he gave them power</hi> (exuſian) <hi>to be made the ſonnes of God.</hi> Io. 2. v. 12. they pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce <hi>Prerogative.</hi> Bible 1558. but novv ſince li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is come into credit, they have reſtored the vvord <hi>Power</hi> Bible 1628. Is this to follow Scripture, or rather force Scripture to follow themſelves? But to be ſure their wives may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv them, they make <hi>S. Paul</hi> vvandring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the vvorld like a <hi>German Souldier</hi> with his vvife behind him. 1. Cor. 9. v. 5. <hi>Have not we power to lead about a wife being a ſiſter</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble 1580. and this remaines vnchanged even in the Bible 1628. and is like to remaine till Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be weary of their wiues. Notwithſlanding S. <hi>Paul</hi> a litle before c. 7. v. 8. ſufficiently giveth to be vnderſtood, he was not married. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding S. <hi>Hiorome</hi> interprets it, and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> proves it to be, not wife, but woeman, and the Greeke fathers moſt expreſſely. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſlanding, theſe very Bibles a litle before c. 7. v. 1. tranſlate woeman, not wife vpon the ſame Greeke word, and without any article, or particle of difference betwixt the ſame word in both places, ſaving that it was not for their purpoſe to make S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay it were good for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not to touch a wife. Notwithſlanding that all who know Spanish, Portugues, Italian, French, Hebrew, High, or Low dutch, in which languages the ſame word no leſſe then in Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſignifies both woeman, and wife, are not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106316:72"/>ignorant that whereſoever there is no more determinative ſignes then in the text of S. <hi>Paul</hi> it is generally vnderſtood for a woeman, not wife. And this their lewd humour makes them have ſuch a ſpite againſt the ever Virgin Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God. They could tranſlate (Helcome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos) <hi>full of ſores</hi> Luc. 16. v. 20. ſpeaking of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, but (Kecharitomene) Luc. 1. v. 28. muſt not be <hi>full of grace,</hi> but freely beloved Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble 1628. becauſe it was ſpoken of the Virgin Mother, and in the margen is put <hi>received into favour,</hi> as if the Greeke word were capable of many ſenſes but by no meanes, of that ſenſe which might ſignify that the mother of God being à Virgin should befull of grace. So much she hath loſt in the opinion of theſe lewd fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes vpon the prerogative of her Virginity.</p>
            <p>After their fraud occaſioned by a falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ambiguity, they fall vpon downe right falſity. Where both the Greeke and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin have 1. Cor. 11. v. 27. <hi>Who ſo ever shall eato this bread, or drinke the cup</hi> They put, <hi>and</hi> inſteed of <hi>(or)</hi> Bible 628. to perſuade the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that Catholickes gaineſay the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in not giving allwayes the communion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kinds. But it is no marvel they ſould change <hi>or</hi> into <hi>and</hi> when <hi>Beza</hi> had changed as into <hi>ſignifies</hi> and the German heretiques <hi>ſolum</hi> for <hi>ſoli</hi> to make David ſay, <hi>I have nothing els but ſinned,</hi> in lieu of, <hi>To thee alone I have ſinned.</hi> Pſ. 51. And Luther added the word <hi>alone</hi> to faith, and ſaid it should ſtand in ſpite of all that oppoſed it. But what are theſe changes to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106316:73"/>the making whole bookes Apocryphal becauſe prejudicial to their errours. The Machabees thruſt out vpon account of Purgatory, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticus of liberty, Toby of the aſſiſtance of Angels. For, as to their having bin queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it is a vaine excuſe, ſeing the Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, no leſſe queſtioned, is held for good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſerves the Miniſters to foole the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the hornes of the beaſt planted on the Popes head which would become their own much better. But it is ridiculous to ſee theſe petty Grammarians ſo Critical in the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical ſenſe that Baptiſme muſt be washing, Prieſt, Elder, Beelzebub, Lord of afly, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Vniverſal, and yet <hi>Paradoſis</hi> muſt not be traditions 2. Theſſ. 2. v. 15. but inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions Bible 1628. or ordinances, preachings, inſtitutions, or any thing, but what it should be; yet where mention is made of reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble traditions, you shall be ſure to have this word to English the ſame <hi>Paradoſis</hi> as Matt. 15, v. 2. &amp; 3. of the ſame Bible. Nay you shall have Traditions where the Greeke word is neyther <hi>Paradoſis,</hi> nor any thing like: for; Col. 2. v 20. by <hi>(Tidogmatizeſthe)</hi> any one that knowes the Greeke language, is rather put in mind of Decrees, Doctrines; or opinions, then Traditions; but to make them odious they are left where any thing is ſpoken to their commendation, although the original Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke deliver them in their proper word, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they are thruſt in by head and shoulders, where the Greeke hath a word very different,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106316:73"/>and this not onely in the old Bible 1579. <hi>are you led with traditions?</hi> but in a later 1628. <hi>are you burdened with Traditions?</hi> The Greeke ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no word proper to Traditions, much leſſe to burdening. I wonder the tranſlater of this late Bible was not ashamed here as in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place for 2. Cor. 6. v. 16. he puts, as he ought, <hi>what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols,</hi> not daring to be ſo impudent, as to follow the Bible 1567. <hi>How agreeth the Temple of God with images,</hi> being a thing known that, ever the Iews Temples wanted not images. Much more of this kind, and even more sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull profanation you may ſee M. <hi>Bramhall</hi> in <hi>Gregory Martin,</hi> whoſe authority, though you ſlight, yet you ought not to ſlight the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, and manifeſt examples he brings. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the authority of your Brethren the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, whom you now, and then find occaſion to flatter in your bookes, vvill be of more weight with you, or at leaſt with others. In a petition directed to her moſt excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp;c. pag they ſpeake in theſe termes. <hi>Our tranſlation of the Pſalmes compriſed in the booke of common prayer doth in addition, ſubtraction, and alteration differ from the truth of the Hebrew in two thous and places at leaſt. And M.</hi> Carliele <hi>a Proteſtant, in his booke that Chriſt deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, ſayth of the English tranſlaters, that they have depraved the ſenſe, obſcured the truth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved the ignorant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir I hope you vvill be pleaſed, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to take notice of the argument which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106316:74"/>you paſſed by vvinking, as if it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be regarded. Miniſters falſify Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, no wonder if they forge records. They are ſo deprived of conſcience, and shame, that they conſpire to maintaine their religion with <hi>John Foxes</hi> moſt falſe, and foolish ſtories, with moſt impudent falſifications of Scripture, of ancient, and moderne Authors, which any man that will take the leaſt paines may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſee to be wilfull, vnconſcionable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable; therefore no marvel if they give falſe atteſtations of a matter not extant in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and which may after ſo long a time have bin forgot by ſome, and remembred by others, who are not preſſed to teſtify their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as being a thing needles to the cauſe, and dangerous to their perſons. You thought that as one mans yawning makes others yavvne, ſo your winking at this argument, would make others winke, and not marke the force of it. You hoped to perſuade the Reader that you might as lawfully reject my Authors, as I yours. As if there were no difference bewixt men of true, and falſe dealing. Let any man judge that is acquainted with <hi>Stapleton, Belar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Parſons, Peron,</hi> shew in any of them ſuch fowle, and wilfull cheating, as manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in <hi>Jewel, Morton, Andrews Barlow,</hi> and generally in the reſt of the prime Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſters, or if he be not acquainted with our writers, let him but pervſe the aforeſaid <hi>Walſinghams</hi> ſearch into Religion, or the Quiet, and ſober reckoning with M. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106316:74"/>Morton,</hi> where he shall find Proteſtants never more falſe, then in their imputation of falſood to our Authors. In whom I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſcover any wilfull corruption in defenſe of our Religion againſt heretiques, and the Author of the Treatiſe tending to Mitigation, a man well verſed in the writings, of both ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, hath c. 12. pag. 489. long ſince challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Morton to bring forth any Catholicke Authors whatſoever that wrote againſt Proteſtants ſince theſe hereſies began, that hath bin taken in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, I meane that hath ſet downe in print any ſuch falſity, as can not be excuſed eyther by iguorance, overſight, negligence, error of print, tranſlation, diverſity of editions, or the like; but that it must needs be preſumed that he knew the vntruth, and yet would ſet it forth: of this kind, I ſay, let him shew but one example among all Catholicke writers of our time, and I will in my conſcience greatly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, and diſcredit the Author, whether it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother or my ſelfe. But if he shew me two or three in any writer of this kind I shall never be able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him more.</hi> Thus he. Certainely, if we were given to this practiſe, it vvould have bin di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered in the innumerable citations of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> or of the Author of the Proteſtants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology vvho hath collected the ſayings, of all Proteſtant vvriters, he could poſſibly find. We have vſed faire dealing in the edition of Scripture, we follow, as having bin in vſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages in the Church before theſe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and therefore not fraudalently cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, much leſſe falſely changed to favour our
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106316:75"/>doctrine, which D <hi>Covel</hi> Proteſtant in his anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to M. <hi>John Burges</hi> pag 94. confeſſeth to have bin vſed in the Church a thous and three hundred yeares agoe; where he prefers it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, and pag. 91. prefers amongſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish tranſlations, that vvhich comes neereſt it. Which is highly commended by <hi>Beza</hi> in his Annot. in c. 2 Luc. v. 1. and by <hi>Molinaeus</hi> the famous french Calviniſt, is more eſteemed then the tranſlation of <hi>Eraſmus, Bucer, Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Tigurines,</hi> and of <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe, and all others.</p>
            <p>To conclude, what Proteſtant ſo ever will not take the paines to confer the doctrines, and Doctors of both parties, but vvill take M. <hi>Bramhals</hi> empty words for found arguments, his pretermiſſions for ſolutions, his prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or preſumption for a ſerious, and ſolid defenſion, his Rhetorical Tropes for ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal anſvvers, his negative atteſtations about a ſmal acceſſory, for a poſitive Vindication of the principal charge made againſt his Clergy, ſcraps of Hiſtory, for Chriſtian Theology, a deceitfull appearance of long coates, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſes, for a ſufficient evidence of Prieſtly character, to ſuch a one, I ſay, that he neyther deſerves a more faithfull champion to reſcue him in his dangers, nor a more skilfull Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to reſolve him in his doubts, nor a more lawfull Prieſt to abſolve him from his ſins.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106316:75"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
